斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到2013至2014秋季学期CS193P第九讲
Alright. Well, welcome to Lecture number 9 of CS193P, fall of 2013/14.
今天我会先完成周一开始的
Today I'm going to finish the animation demo
那个动画示例演示
that we started on Monday,
然后这节课的主要内容是autolayout自动布局
and then the lecture's going to be about autolayout,
这是一套非常棒的系统
which is a really cool system for making it
可以让你的用户界面适应变化的环境
so that your user interface can adapt to changing conditions.
最后我会做一个简单的自动布局演示
And then I'll do a brief autolayout demo at the end,
让大家看看实际操作是怎样的
just so you can kind of see it in action.
眼见为实 尤其是自动布局这部分
Seeing is believing, especially with autolayout.
这个示例 我们上次实现了
So this demo, where we left off
让方块在重力作用下掉落
is the blocks would come down due to gravity
在底部碰撞
and they would collide at the bottom
方块相互之间会碰撞
and they'd kind of run into each other,
当底部的一行拼满之后
and then when a bottom row was full
这一行就会飞出去
they would all kind of fly off into outer space.
还留下一个问题就是 它们能够堆积起来
And I think where we left off too was they would stack up
但是不会飞出去
and they weren't flying off, okay?
为什么最后不飞出去呢
And so why weren't they flying off at the end?
部分是因为
Well, part of the reason they weren't flying off was
方块搭成的塔太不稳了
because they were, those towers of blocks were so tippy,
一直在晃动 不会停下来
they were kind of wiggling, they were never coming to rest, okay?
动画永远都不会停下来
So they were never, the animation was never stopping.
始终会小幅度移动着
It was always continuing to move them a little bit,
我们先要对示例进行修改
and so we're going to start off our demo
让方块堆得更稳固一些
by making those stacks a little more solid,
减少摇晃
a little less tippy,
方法是禁止方块旋转
by making it so that the blocks can't rotate.
如果方块不能旋转
So since they can't rotate,
相互叠加得就会更稳固一些
they'll sit on top of each other much nicer
我还要把重力大小设回为1
and I'm gonna turn gravity back up to 1.0,
我之前将它设为了0.9
I think I had typed in .9 at some point,
只应用于这个示例
just as far as the demo,
我们再把它改回去
but let's crank it back up
让方块坐得更稳 完全不会浮起来
so that they will sit a little bit so they don't float at all,
重重地放在其他方块顶部
you know, so they sit down strongly on top of each other.
然后我要使用一个吸附行为
Then what I'm gonna do is use an attachment behavior
这样当方块掉落时 我们就能抓住它了
so as the block falls, we can grab onto it, okay?
然后我们可以让它摆动
And then we can kind of swing it around
选择掉落的堆叠位置
and pick which stack we want to drop it in
然后再让它掉下去
and then let it go.
最后要做的是
And then the last thing I'm gonna do is
使用吸附行为的action block
we're gonna use the action block of that attachment behavior
添加并显示出吸附效果
to animate that and show the attachment,
我要画一条线来显示它
I'm just gonna actually draw a little line to show it.
今天有很多要演示的内容
So it's quite a bit to show there.
我觉得我们没时间
I don't think we're going to have time
演示碰撞委托这部分
to do this collision delegate thing,
但我会上传这部分的代码
but I'll post the code for that
帮助大家学习这部分是怎样实现的
so you can see what that's all about.
好了 我们回到Xcode
Alright, so, let's get back over to Xcode here
回到Dropit中
and go back into Dropit and--
记得吗 我们把示例中的全部行为
Okay, so, remember that we moved all of the behavior
都移到了它自己的一个UIDynamicBehavior子类中
of this thing out into its own subclass of UIDynamicBehavior,
叫做dropitBehavior
called dropitBehavior.
这边这个
Right over here, this guy,
重力和碰撞行为就在这里面
and so that's where the gravity and the collision is.
我要做的是
And so what I'm gonna do there is
向自定义行为中再增加一个行为
I'm gonna add another behavior to that customer behavior,
我们可以通过它控制是否允许方块旋转
which let us control things like whether the blocks rotate.
还可以控制其摩擦力 阻力 密度
Okay? We can also control friction, resistance, density,
这类属性
those kind of things in there.
控制这些属性设置的行为
The kind of behavior that is that controls those things
叫做UIDynamicItemBehavior
is called a UIDynamicItemBehavior,
因为它指定的是动力项的行为
because it's specifying the behavior of that item
这里我们叫它
Okay? So we'll call that,
比如animationOptions
maybe something like animationOptions,
或者类似的名字
or something like that,
你可以叫它itemBehaviors
you can call them itemBehaviors, some,
或者physicalCharacteristics之类的
you might call them physicalCharacteristics almost,
但这里我们就用这个名字了
but that's, we'll do that.
在下面这里添加延迟实例化
And let's go down here and lazy instantiate that,
UIDynamicItemBehavior animationOptions
so dynamic behavior animationOptions.
如果没有animationOptions
If not animationOptions,
animationOptions=[[UIDynamicItemBehavior alloc] init]
then animationOptions equals UIDynamicItemBehavior alloc init.
对它进行配置
So I'm just allocating this thing
将allowRotation设为NO
and I'm going to allowRotation, no.
不允许这些动力项旋转
So I'm not gonna allow these items to rotate.
方块必须保持稳定状态
Okay? So the blocks will have to stay
在互相碰撞 反弹的时候
as they bounce on each other and collide,
不可以旋转
they'll have to stay nonrotated.
然后返回animationOptions
Alright? And return animationOptions.
我们还可以在这里设置
And, again, we can do other things in here
摩擦力和密度等等
like dot friction equals dot density equals whatever,
省点事 我们就不做了
but we'll keep it simple.
当然 要将全部动力项
I obviously want all items to be added
都添加到这个animationOptions中
also to this animationOptions thing
移除动力项也是一样
and we clearly want to remove all items, as well.
最后添加子行为animationOptions
And let's finally add our child behavior animationOptions.
animationOption和其他行为是一样的
So the animationOptions act like any other behavior, okay?
只不过它是在指定属性
They just specify attributes instead of, you know,
而不是应用作用力等
applying the forces or whatever,
但其实你也可以把它们看做是在应用作用力
but you can actually think of them somewhat as applying forces too,
比如 用作用力阻止物体旋转
it's just, you know, like forces to keep them from rotating
或者用作用力增加物体的摩擦力
or forces to make them have higher friction,
可以这样理解
those kind of things.
有问题吗
Okay. Question?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
好问题
What a great question.
你是问 如果有多个动力项行为
You mean if, if you had multiple item behaviors
密度等属性设置有冲突会怎样 是吗
that had different conflicting densities or whatever?
这是个好问题
So that's a great question.
有对应的规则
There are rules for that
如果你有一个行为树
if you have, you know, a tree of behaviors
里面有一些动力项行为
and you had some item behaviors in there.
规则会规定哪个动力项行为起决定作用
There are rules for which one wins,
可能是最后一个
it's kind of the last one wins
是如何发生的
and how that's happens
这些都在文档中定义了
is all defined in the documentation for it,
所以如果你要构建复杂的树形结构
so if you're gonna build a tree so complicated
里面有动力项使用了两次
that you have the items in there twice
两个不同的行为等等
with two different behaviors and different things,
如果你要这样做
I mean, that's pretty, I mean, if you're doing that,
你真的需要清楚自己在做什么
you really got to know what you're doing
你需要查阅文档
and so you really want to read the documentation,
这是行为的高级用法
that would be considered advanced behavior to do that,
但是可以这样做
but it can be done.
是合法的
It is legal.
这样就设置好了
Okay. So, now we'll have that.
现在我们再运行一下
So now when we run this,
这回堆积的方块就不会那么摇晃了
we'll get a little less of the tippy stack thing,
但是我没有修改重力大小
although I didn't change the gravity,
我们先看看目前的效果
but we'll see what happens here,
可以看到 它们没有转动
but you can see they're definitely not twisting,
垂直落在其他方块顶部
they're staying.
它们可能还是会稍微弹向一边
They still might bounce slightly to the side if they--
比如当我快速点击时
for example, if I clicked too fast
方块下落时就可能会相撞
they might crash into each other on the way down,
如果它们都在同一列的话
once that they are in the same column.
拼满一行了
So here we go.
现在 就能更可靠地
So now, they're gonna
显示飞走的效果了
to be flying away a little more reliably.
我们再试试快速点击
Let's try going really fast,
看看能不能让它们倾斜一点
see if we can get them to tip a little.
如果拼满多行 这几行会一块飞出去
Now I, if I have multiple rows, they should all go together.
还要注意 随着方块数量的增加
Notice also I'm starting to get a lot of blocks
应用开始变得磕磕绊绊的了
and it's the performance that's starting to get a little jerky.
这是需要大家理解的一点
Okay? And that's something you have to understand
在动画时 如果要为很多对象添加动画
when animation, if you have a lot of things animated,
并非免费的
it's not free.
动画是要占用资源的
Okay? Animation is not free.
如果你的应用像这里一样
And if you had an application like this
让方块掉落下来
where you were dropping these blocks
允许用户掉落很多方块
and you allowed the user to drop a lot of them,
你可能需要进行一些其他处理
you might have to start doing some other things,
比如 修改碰撞边界
like, for example, instead of having the collision boundary,
不让所有动力项相互碰撞
instead of having all the items collide with each other,
而是沿着顶部绘制一条边界
what if you just drew a boundary around the top
让顶部的方块进行碰撞
that they top ones could collide to.
这样 底部的方块
You see? Then you would keep all those bottom ones
就不用再一直计算自己的移动位置
from having to calculate where they're going to go,
因为你会注意到
because you'll notice that
当它们被压在底下之后
after they get tamped down a little bit,
就不会出现太多的弹跳了
they don't bounce so much at the bottom anyways,
所以你可以取消弹跳 放置一个边界
so you could take away that bounce and put a boundary,
边界是一个UIBezierPath
because your boundary is a UIBezierPath,
可以是任意形状
it can be anything you want.
如果要处理的动画对象太多
Okay? So you have to think about that only, you know,
你就要考虑这个问题
when you start getting to extreme cases there.
好了 同学们
Okay, everyone.
有问题吗
Cool with that?
都明白了吗
Make sense?
我们最后要做的是
Alright, so, the last thing we're gonna do
吸附行为
is this attachment behavior.
就是吸附一条杆
So this is just attaching that bar,
可以是有弹性的或者是一条铁杆
which can be a springy bar or an iron bar,
我要用一条铁杆
I'm going to leave mine be an iron bar,
既不会塌陷 也不会伸长
you know, a bar that doesn't collapse and expand.
我们要用这条杆抓住掉落的方块
And, we will use that bar to grab onto one that's coming down
这样就能将其摆动至目标列中
so I can swing it into the right column,
目前是方块出现在哪一列
because right now it's just whatever column it comes down in,
就落在那一列
that's the column it goes in
感觉有点限制性
and that's a little bit restrictive,
影响我的游戏的竞争力
it makes it hard for my game to play very, very competitively.
我们要做的是
And so, what we're gonna do to do this,
我们需要在视图控制器中增加一些东西
we need a couple of things here, in our view controller.
首先我们显然需要一个吸附行为
One is we're gonna clearly need an attachment behavior,
我要新建一个UIAttachmentBehavior
so I'm gonna create a new UIAttachmentBehavior.
我就叫它attachment
I'm just going to call it attachment, okay?
我还需要知道掉落的是哪个视图
And, I'm also gonna need to know which view is dropping.
当前正在掉落的视图
Okay? The view that's currently falling down
因为我要抓住的就是这个视图
because that's the one I'm going to grab on.
游戏中有一大堆视图
Because there's a whole bunch of views in my game, right?
这些视图都堆在那里
Tons of them, all of them are stacked up there,
当我开始抓取时 我要抓住哪个
which one, when I start grabbing, am I gonna grab onto?
就是这个droppingView
It's gonna be the droppingView,
所以我要追踪正在掉落的视图
so I'm gonna have to keep track of the dropping view
实际上 很容易追踪
and, in fact, that's easy to keep track of,
就写在下面这里 每次掉落一个新的视图时
I'll just write down here, every time I drop a new one,
就让droppingView等于dropView
I'm gonna say the droppingView equals the dropView.
这样每次新视图掉落时
Okay? So every time a new one comes down,
这个视图就是被抓取的视图
it's gonna become the one that gets grabbed.
如果同时掉落多个视图
So if I have multiple of them coming down at once,
那么就是最后一个掉落的视图
it's the last one that started coming down
成为被抓取的对象
is gonna be the one that gets grabbed,
用这个吸附行为进行抓取
if I grab onto it with this attachment.
现在我得到了droppingView
Okay? So now I have the droppingView.
我要用一个拖动手势实现吸附操作
So, I'm gonna do the attachment with a pan gesture.
所以这里我们会见到另一个手势识别器
Okay? So we're gonna see another gesture recognizer here,
我要抓住它
because I'm gonna grab it
然后随着手指在屏幕上的移动
and then as I move my finger around on the screen,
让吸附对象吸附着我的手指
I'm gonna keep the attachment attached to my finger.
所以被抓住的那个方块
So the block that's being grabbed onto it
会随着我的手指移动
it will kind of follow my finger around, right?
二者中间有一条杆连着
With the bar behind it.
很有意思
So, that'll be kind of fun.
我们来做一下
So let's do that.
大家还记得如何设置手势吧
So you'll remember the gestures we set up, right,
在storyboard中进行设置 这是storyboard
from our storyboard, right, here's the storyboard.
我要到这边抓取一个手势
I'm gonna go over and grab a gesture,
拖动手势 代表随着手指移动
it's a pan gesture, which means follow the finger around,
拖动手势在这里
so here's a pan gesture.
拖出它  直接放在gameView上面
Drag this out, I'm just gonna drag it on top of my gameView,
就放在上面这里
right on top here.
这是我的点击手势和拖动手势
Here's my tap gesture, here's my pan gesture,
我要把它拖出来
so I'm gonna drag it out,
放到点击手势这边
I'm gonna put it down near where my tap gesture is.
点击手势在这里
Here's my tap gesture right here,
我就把拖动手势放在它下面
so I'm gonna put my pan gesture right next to it.
我要叫它pan
I'm going to call it pan,
我可能示范了不好的命名样式
I'm probably teaching a bad style here
直接叫它们pan和tap
to call these pan and tap,
我用这种名字是为了让大家明白
I call them that so that when you see them you realize,
这是拖动手势处理器
oh yeah, that's the pan gesture handler,
也可以叫做grabDrop等类似的名字
but again, this could be something like grabDrop,
这种名字可能更适合这个拖动手势
that might be a better name for this than pan.
明白吗
Okay?
这就是我们的手势
So, there's our gesture and--
扩大点空间
let's make some more space
实际上 我们不需要...
and actually we don't even need to see--
回到这里
actually let's go back here.
这里我们不需要查看storyboard
We don't need to see our storyboard for this.
拖动手势在这里
Okay? So I've got my pan right here.
这个拖动手势中会发生什么呢
So what's gonna happen in this pan?
拖动手势和捏合手势
Okay, pan gestures, like pinch gestures,
以及其他类似连续手势
and continuous gestures like that,
事件执行顺序类似
they kind of have a similar sequence of events that goes on,
我有一小段代码
so I have a little snippet
适用于所有这类手势
that I do the same thing for all these kind of gestures,
开始时状态为Began
which is they start out, they begin,
随着移动 状态变为Changed
then they change as they move around
然后结束时状态为Ended
and then they end.
执行吸附行为时
So what are the three things we're going to do
拖动手势要做的三件事是什么呢
for our pan gesture when we do our attachment?
首先 我要做的是
Well, the first thing I'm going to do,
实际上 我要做的第一件事是
actually the first thing I'm going to do
找到拖动手势的位置
is I'm going to find out where is that pan gesture?
发生在gameView的什么位置呢
Where did that happen in my gameView?
方法是
And I'm going to do that with
CGPoint gesturePoint=[sender locationInView:gameView]
CGPoint, gesturePoint equals sender locationInView, my gameView.
这样我就可以知道手势在gameView中发生的位置
Okay, so now I know where in my gameView that happens.
这是个手势识别器 对吧
So this is a gesture recognizer, right?
这是sender 这是拖动手势处理器的一个方法
This sender is and this's a method in pan gesture recognizer,
能够告诉你拖动手势发生的位置
which tells you the location the pan happened
如果手势正在移动
or is happening if it's moving around,
它会告诉你最新的当前位置
it tells you the new position.
这里我先要做的是
So, the first thing I'm going to do
将刚才说过的droppingView
is I'm going to attach the droppingView,
吸附到发生手势的那个点上
that thing we just said, to that point.
gesturePoint这个点
The gesturePoint.
这个方法我们要实现一下
Okay? So this is a method we're going to have to write,
放到下面这里 这样我们就不会忘记实现它了
so we'll put it down here so that we remember to do it.
但是如果我们不在这里增加这个方法
Though we might, we might remember better
可能更不会忘
if we don't put this down here, but,
因为系统会不断提示
because it'll keep complaining.
这里先加上了
We'll do that.
我要让它与droppingView吸附
So I'm going to have this attached to droppingView,
这是使用吸附行为的主要内容
that's going to the guts of doing an attachment thing.
当拖动手势变化时 当它移动到一个新位置时
Here, when the pan changes, when it moves to a new spot,
我要将吸附行为的anchorPoint...
I'm just going to have my attachment behavior anchorPoint,
还记得锚点吗
okay, anchor point, remember,
吸附行为可以是两个动力项吸附
the attachment can be either attachment between two items
或者是动力项和锚点吸附
or between an anchor point in an item.
这里是动力项与锚点吸附
This is going to be between an anchor point,
锚点会随着我的手指移动
that anchor point is going to be following my finger around.
我要将它设为gesturePoint
I'm going to set that to be the gesturePoint, okay?
这就是手势发生变化时 我要做的操作
So that's all I'm going to do when it changes.
然后 当它完成时
And then, when it's done,
我要移除这个吸附行为
I'm going to do remove this attachment,
用removeBehavior将attachment从animator中移除
removeBehavior, this attachment from my animator.
动画者会停止继续执行这个动画
So my animator is gonna stop doing that animation anymore.
就是这样
Okay? So that's it.
可以看到 这些都很简单
You can see this is all pretty easy to do, all this stuff.
这个attach方法也非常简单
Even this attach is going to be really straightforward.
我们来看一下这个方法
So let's look at that attach.
如何在一个锚点和某个动力项之间
How do we create an attachment behavior
创建吸附行为呢
between an anchor point and some item?
非常简单
And it's very simple.
如果有一个正在掉落的动力项
If we have an item that's currently dropping, okay,
希望有一个
hopefully we do,
然后我们只要新建一个吸附行为
then we're just gonna create a new attachment behavior
用UIAttachmentBehavior alloc init
with UIAttachmentBehavior alloc, and its init,
有四个不同的init方法
it has, remember, four different kinds of inits here,
取决于你要创建的是锚点与动力项的吸附行为
depending on whether you're attaching the points
还是两个动力项的吸附行为
or between two items.
还可以吸附到一个偏移位置上
It also has some ways to attach with an offset
这样连接铁杆就不会连接到物体中心
so that the iron bar is not connected to the center of the thing,
中心会偏移一点
maybe it's centered a little offset,
物体会略微倾斜
it'll tilt a little bit.
我要用的是initWithItem attachedToAnchor
So I'm gonna do the one which is initWithItem attachedToAnchor,
应该是这个
which is this one I guess,
动力项就是那个droppingView
and the item is going to be that droppingView.
错了 不是吸附到动力项上
Oops, sorry, attach to item, no,
我想要的是吸附到锚点上
I wanted a different one, I want attach to anchor.
锚点就是刚才的那个点
And the anchor is going to be that point, right,
拖动手势触摸的位置
where my tap pan gesture went down.
就是这些 就是这么简单
So that's it, it's as simple as that,
我创建了一个吸附行为
and now I have an attachment
吸附了那个点和掉落视图droppingView
between that point and this droppingView,
锚点随着手势的移动而移动
I'm gonna be moving that point as the gesture moves,
droppingView会跟在它后面移动
and the droppingView is just gonna follow around.
吸附行为发生以后
After that attachment happens, by the way,
就不允许再次操作了
I'm not going to allow you to do it again,
所以我要将droppingView设为nil
so I'm going to set the droppingView to nil.
换句话说
Okay? So in other words,
不允许你抓住一个方块
I'm not going to let you grab onto that thing,
移动一点 掉了 然后再次抓住移动
move it a little, oops, grab onto it again, move it again,
不行 你只能移动一次
nope, you get one try, okay
这是游戏规则的一部分
that's just part of the game play,
只允许对掉落方块操作一次
I only want you to get one try dropping that thing.
然后只要用animator addBehavior
And then I just say, animator, addBehavior,
这样做之后 就会开始动画
and instantly I do this it's going to start animating that.
为那个锚点和视图之间的连接
Okay? Animating an anchor, a connection
添加动画
between that point and that, that view.
这就是我要做的全部内容
Okay? So, I think that's all that I have to do.
运行一下 看是否运行正常
So let's run and see if this works.
一个方块掉下来了
Alright, so we have them dropping down,
我抓住它 可以看到鼠标的移动
I grabbed onto it, you see how, you see my mouse,
我好像抓住了它的手柄
you can see how I kind of have a hold of it
像是一条杆 我甚至可以将它顶在上面
and it's like a bar, I can even, whoa, balance it on top?
有点不容易看清楚
You see? It's a little hard to see, right?
我们应该画一条线
So maybe we'll draw a line
连接吸附点和方块
between the attachment point and the little thing.
懂吗
Okay?
所以这就是我下面要做的事情
So that's the next thing I'm going to do
绘制一条线
is I'm gonna draw a line between where I'm panning and the--
连接拖动手势位置和掉落项
and the item that I'm dropping.
我们来做一下
So let's do that.
这样做的原因
And I'm doing that not as much,
不仅是为了演示吸附行为的工作原理
partially to show you how the attachment is working,
还是为了演示action的使用方法
but also because I want to show you how to use this action,
大家可以使用的这个action block
this little action block that you can use.
我要如何绘制呢
So, how am I going to draw that?
要如何绘制这条线呢
Okay? How am I going to draw this line?
我要做的是
Well, what I'm gonna do is
将这里的storyboard的gameView
I'm going to make the gameView of my storyboard here
变为UIBezierPath绘制视图
be a UIBezierPath Drawing view.
我要新建一种视图
Okay? So I'm going to create a new kind of view,
选择新建文件
oops, new file.
它是UIView的一个子类
And it's going to be a UIView, subclass a UIView,
我要叫它BezierPathView
I'm going to call it BezierPathView,
它会是一个完全通用的
okay? And this is going to be a totally generic,
贝塞尔曲线绘制视图
Bezier path drawing view,
所以在它的公有API中
so it's public API is,
有一个公有属性
it is going to have one property, public property,
是一个UIBezierPath 叫做path
which is a UIBezierPath, called path.
这就是它的整个公有API
Alright? That's its entire public API,
它只要在drawRect中
and all its gonna do is in its drawRect,
用path stroke
it is going to say path stroke.
我只要再...
Okay? And the only other thing I'm going to do is--
是self.path
self dot path,
我只要再做一件事 就是在setPath中
and the only other thing I'm gonna do here is in setPath,
这是它的setter
the setter for that thing,
在里面写_path=path
I'm going to do underline path equals path,
self setNeedsDisplay
and I'm going to say self setNeedsDisplay.
只要有人修改了path 就会重绘
So anytime someone changes the path, it's going to redraw it.
大家明白这个类是做什么的了吗
Okay? Everyone understand what this class does?
希望大家都明白了
I hope, right?
这将大家知道的全部绘制的内容
It combines everything you know
都结合在了一起
about drawing, right, in one thing.
DrawRect BezierPath描边 setNeedsDisplay
DrawRect, BezierPath stroking, setNeedsDisplay,
全部内容 就是这样
the whole thing, so that's it.
现在我要回到storyboard
Now, I'm going to go back to my storyboard
这个gameView现在是UIView类
and I'm gona have this gameView, instead of being a UIView,
我要将它的类变为BezierPathView
I'm going to change its class to be BezierPathView.
大家都记得吧 我讲过的
Okay? So everyone remember what I told you about,
如果你有一个这样的自定义视图
if you have a custom view like this,
刚拖出来时 它是一个通用视图
it starts out generic when you drag it out,
最开始是通用的
right, it starts out generic,
你可以修改它的类 就像控制器一样
and you can change its class, just like with the controller.
为了让控制器中代码匹配
Okay? Now, to match this up in my controller,
我最好将上面这里修改一下
I better go up here and say that this is a--
我的gameView在哪呢
where is that thing, my gameView,
将它改为BezierPathView
is a BezierPathView,
这里要加一下
so let's do that.
BezierPathView
BezierPathView.
这里是BezierPathView
Alright. So it's BezierPathView,
这样我就可以向它发送贝塞尔曲线消息了
so that I can send it BezierPath messages, okay?
现在我的gameView可以显示任意贝塞尔曲线
Alright, so now my gameView can display an arbitrary BezierPath,
现在我只要计算贝塞尔曲线
so now all I have to do is calculate the BezierPath between--
吸附行为要显示的贝赛尔曲线
that the attachment shows,
也就是锚点和掉落视图间的连线
basically, between the anchor point and the dropping view,
每次吸附视图变化时
and then every time that attachment view changes,
我都要对其重绘 重置路径
I have to redraw, I have to reset that path,
每次都要重新计算
recalculate it every time.
这也就是action block
Okay, so that's where this action block
要起作用的地方
is going to come into play.
我们要怎么做呢
Alright? So, how are we going to do that?
我们在这个方法中实现
Let's do it right in here, okay?
当我们在这里创建这个吸附行为时
When we attach, when we create this attachment right here,
我们要使用它的action block
we are going to use the little action block of this guy,
来更新它
action, to update that thing,
首先是脱字符号^ 然后是大括号
so, let's go caret, curly brace, curly brace,
这是声明block的方法
okay, this is how we specify a block.
我们要将这段代码传递给attachment
So we're gonna pass this block of code off to this attachment,
每次动画时
and every time it animates,
就会调用这段代码
it's gonna call this block of code,
我们要在这段代码中做什么呢
and what are we going to do in this block of code?
我们要创建一个贝赛尔曲线
Well, we're going to create a BezierPath.
[[UIBezierPath alloc] init]
Just using UIBezierPath alloc init.
这个贝塞尔曲线需要有一个目标移动位置
And this BezierPath needs to have a move to,
我们就让它移动到吸附行为的锚点
so let's have it move to the anchor point of the attachment,
也就是self.attachment.anchorPoint
so that's self dot attachment dot anchorPoint.
然后用path addLineToPoint
And then we're gonna path add line to,
向掉落视图的位置添加连线
we need to go to where the dropping view is.
也就是self.droppingView.center
That's self dot droppingView dot center.
现在我们有了路径
Alright? And now we have that path
我只要用self.gameView.path=path
so I can just say self dot gameView dot path equals path.
有问题吗
Okay? Any questions about this?
请讲
Yeah?
[学生提问]
Student:[inaudible]
问题是
Yeah, so the question is
不可以直接在这里用anchorPoint吗
couldn't I just say right here anchorPoint?
因为我在这里传递了anchorPoint
Because I'm passing anchorPoint right here.
答案是不行 不能这样做
And the answer is no, I can't do that,
因为anchorPoint一直在变化
because I'm changing the anchorPoint, right?
每次拖动手势移动时 都会修改锚点
Every time you move that pan, I'm changing that anchor point.
每次发生时 这段代码都会被执行
So, this block of code gets executed every time it happens,
所以我不能使用这个anchorPoint
so I can't use this anchorPoint,
它只在第一次吸附时被传递进来
which was only passed in here when I first attached it.
我得用self.attachment.anchorPoint
I have to use self dot attachment dot anchorPoint.
也就是
In other words, the anchor,
锚点当前吸附的那一点
the anchor point's current attachment point.
所以我必须不断调用它
Right? So that's why I have to keep calling that.
请讲
Yeah?
你在设置block之后
Since you setting self dot droppingView to nil
将self.droppingView设为了nil
after you set that block
这会影响block内的操作吗
will that affect what happens in the block?
非常好的问题
Yeah. Excellent question.
我将这个self.droppingView设为了nil
So, I'm setting this self dot droppingView to nil
我还在里面使用了self.droppingView
and I'm using self dot droppingView in here.
不会出问题吗
Isn't that going to break it?
答案是 当然会的
And the answer is absolutely it is.
我是故意这样做的
Okay, I did this intentionally,
因为我想告诉大家
because I wanted to show you
这里面的内容
that the things that are in here
每次都会被重新评估
get reevaluated every time,
每次动画发生时 这个block都会被执行
this block gets executed each time animation happens.
那要怎么办呢
So how can I deal with that?
可以直接
Well, I can just,
在这里新建一个局部变量
how about create a little local variable here
叫做droppingView 让它等于self.droppingView
called droppingView equals self dot droppingView,
然后在这里用这个局部变量
and then I will use that right here.
这样我是在这里用局部变量抓取了droppingView
Okay? So now I've captured the droppingView, here,
然后在这里使用
in a local variable, and I'm using it here.
所以这里用的是这个局部变量
So this is referring to this local variable,
而不再是self.droppingView了
not to self dot droppingView anymore,
我将它设为nil也没关系
and the fact that I set this to nil doesn't matter.
它还是会指向目标对象
This one's still going to be pointing to that thing.
我只是想演示一下
Okay? So that, I just wanted to kind of show you
block是如何获取
how blocks capture the local variables
范围之外的局部变量的
that are just outside their scope.
实际上 这里还有个问题
Now, we have another problem in here, in fact,
编译器警告我们了 看到了吗
the compiler's warning us about it, you see?
在此block中对self使用强引用
Capturing self strongly in this block
可能会导致保留循环
is likely to lead to a retain cycle.
就是我们说过的存储循环
That's a memory cycle like we were talking about.
实际上 确实会的
And, in fact, it's going to.
因为这个action block是在这个attachment中的
Because this action, this block, is inside this attachment,
被attachment强引用 而attachment又被self强引用
strongly held by it, which is strongly held by us,
所以我们有一个指向block的强指针
so we have a strong pointer to the block,
如果在这里使用self
and if I put self in here,
block就会有一个指向self的强指针
the block is going to have a strong pointer to us,
这样就不好了
and that's no good.
所以我们要使用这个技巧
So we're going to do this trick,
双下划线weak 叫什么来着
underbar, underbar weak UI-- what do we call,
它叫什么
what is the name of this thing?
DropitViewController 这就是self
DropitViewController, that's our self.
weakSelf=self
WeakSelf equals self.
这样我就创建了一个指向self的弱指针
So now I've created a weak pointer to myself,
然后我就可以在这里使用它了
and now I can use that here.
weakSelf
WeakSelf.
还有下面这里
Okay? Also down here.
weakSelf 明白吗
WeakSelf. Alright?
如果我从堆中被释放
So if I ever got dropped out of the heap,
没有强指针指向我了
and no one had a strong pointer to me,
weakSelf指针就会变为nil
these weakSelf pointers would all go to nil,
但这是没问题的
but that would be fine,
因为如果我不在
because if I'm not around,
那这个action也没什么意义了 对吧
then this action doesn't mean anything anyway, right?
我是控制器
I'm the controller.
所以这样做完全没问题
So, so it's all perfectly fine to do that.
对刚才这部分有问题吗
Okay? Any questions about what we did there?
这也是需要理解的重要内容
Because that's an important thing to understand, as well.
我们要做的最后一件事是
Alright. One last thing we have to do is
当这个拖动手势结束时
when the gesture ends, the pan gesture ends,
移除动画者
and we remove the animator,
具体代码是
we're going to want to say
self.gameView.path=nil
self dot gameView dot path equals nil.
因为这个action...
Okay? Because this action--
当这里移除之后
once this thing is removed from here,
这个action就不会再执行了
this action is not going to execute anymore,
不会再执行一次action
so we're not gonna get that last action
什么都不绘制 对吧
that draws nothing, right?
我们不希望把那条线留在屏幕上
We don't want that line to be left there.
为了让大家理解
Okay? In fact, here, just to make sure you understand this,
我把它先注释掉 看会发生什么
I'll leave this out and we'll see what happens.
方块掉下来了 看
Okay, so I'm dropping here and now, see,
我撑住了这条杆
look, I've got my bar.
可以来回移动 掉落在目标位置
Dance this thing around, drop it where I want.
看到了吗 这条线没有消失
Oh, see the bar didn't go away.
因为action没被调用
Okay? Because that action never called,
因为这行代码
that's because of this line of codes,
取消注释 再运行一次
so let's put this back, now we'll run.
掉下来一个 抓住它 又掉下来一个
Okay, now we drop one, we got it, drop another one,
又掉下来一个 从旁边抓住 又一个
another one, grab onto the side, another one,
可以让它旋转
try and swing it around.
如果我们让它转起来 撞到这里
Okay, if we swing it around and smash it in there,
它们依旧会产生碰撞效果
they'll still collide.
碰撞依然发生
Okay? These are still collision, still happening,
还可以看到
and you can see also that our game
游戏目前有点问题
has a little bit of a problem right now,
对了 它不能旋转
by the way, this not being able to rotate
所以不会翻下来
is why it didn't tip off there.
因为它...
Okay? Because it kind of got, with being,
某个动力项行为阻止了它翻下来
some item behavior is keeping it from tipping off, okay?
目前不是个好游戏
So, this is, by a bad far, game,
因为很难让这些方块排列在底部
because how are we ever gonna line these blocks up here, right?
下面我们要做的呢
So the next thing we would want to do,
我没时间做了
and this is what I'm not gonna do because time here
就是碰撞 当碰撞发生时
is in the collisions, okay, when collisions happen,
碰撞也有一个委托
collisions have a delegate, as well.
在委托中 你要做的是每次...
And in that delegate, what could you do is every time--
碰撞委托可以告诉你碰撞何时开始
and the collision delegate tells you when a collision starts
何时不再处理
and when the collision is ended being processed.
在结束处理程序中
Okay? And in that ending handler,
碰撞向碰撞委托
the ending message that gets sent by the collision
发送的结束消息中
to this collision delegate,
在那个方法中 你要将方块进行排列
in that ending thing, you would then grid the thing up.
也许可以检查一下它的线速度
Probably look at its linear velocity,
如果它在向右移动
if it's moving to the right,
就向右多移一些 让它排列对齐
move it to the right a little more until it lines up.
如果它向左移动
If it's moving to the left,
就向左多移一些 让它排列对齐
move it to the left a little more until it lines up.
代码不多
See? So, not too many lines of code,
但我今天想把自动布局讲完
but I want to make sure we cover autolayout today
所以课上就不继续演示了
so we won't do it, but--
刚才的演示有什么问题吗
any questions about what we did so far or what we did here?
好的
Okay.
那我们就来讲一下自动布局
Alright, so let's get on to the lecture about autolayout.
keynote在哪呢 这呢
Where is my keynote, there it is.
什么是自动布局呢
So what is autolayout?
自动布局是设置所有视图框架的
So autolayout is a way of setting the frame
一种方法
of all your views, okay?
可以是用代码创建的视图框架
And these can be frames of views that you make in code
也可以是拖进storyboard中的框架
or frames that you drag out into your storyboard, okay?
但是我要提醒一下
Although I'll warn you for your homework,
作业中用代码创建的卡牌的框架
the frames of the cards that you make in code,
最好不要使用自动布局
you're probably not gonna wanna use autolayout
来进行布局
to lay those out,
你要使用
you're going to want to use, like,
我提供的grid类或你自己编写的类
that grid class I gave you or some class you write.
因为它们的布局规则
Okay? Because the rules for laying them out
超出了自动布局的功能范围
are kind of beyond even what autolayout can do.
这只是一点提醒
Okay? So that's just a little hint there.
但是全部其他视图
But all the other views, every other, every single other view,
包括容纳卡牌的那个视图
including the view that contains your cards,
都要使用自动布局
you'll want to use autolayout
来决定其在屏幕上的显示位置
to decide where it gets put on screen.
框架的位置将取决于规则
So we're going to decide where to put these frames
而不再是数字
using rules instead of using numbers,
不用再说 将它放到20,20的位置 180宽200高
instead of saying, putting it 20, 20, 180 wide by 200 high,
我们要用规则来决定框架的位置
we're going to use rules to decide where it goes, okay?
这些规则灵活又强大
And these rules are really flexible and powerful,
大部分是关于
and the rules are mostly about the relationship
两个视图间的关系
between one view to another view
或者视图与其父视图之间的关系
or between a view to its superview.
为什么我们要用规则而不是数字
Okay, now why do we want to specify these frames
来指定这些框架的位置呢
as rules instead of as numbers?
因为包含全部视图的矩形边框
Because sometimes the bounding rectangle
有时会变化
that contains all our views is changing.
可能是因为设备旋转了
Either because device rotated,
iPhone屏幕高度不同
we're on a tall iPhone versus a short iPhone,
是否嵌入导航控制器
we're embedded inside of a navigation controller or not,
是否有选项卡栏
we're in a tab view bar or not,
或者是在iPad的弹出窗口控制器视图中
we're on an iPad in some popover controller view
等类似情况
or something like that,
有很多原因可能会导致边框大小变化
there's a lot of reasons that are bounds would change size,
所以我们想要让视图
so we want to build our views
能够对其内容自动调整
so that what's inside of them adjust automatically.
这是作业中很重要的一部分
Okay? And that's part of, a big part of your assignment,
你的卡牌视图
although, your views want to, in terms of your card view,
本来就是要自动调整的
want to adjust automatically anyway,
因为你一直在添加和移除卡牌
because you're adding and removing cards from them
所以它们必须要调整布局
and so they have to adjust anyway,
这里的自动布局有点像是白得的
so you kind of get, probably get that for free,
但是所有其他视图
but all the rest of your views,
重新发牌和得分等等
the one that says redeal and score and all that,
在旋转设备时 要使用自动布局
you're going to want to use autolayout to make those
让它们正确显示在合适位置上
fit in the right place when you rotate the phone.
这些规则
Now, there, these rules,
我们叫做constraints约束 布局约束
by the way, we call them constraints, layout constraints,
我说约束时
so that, when I use the word constraints,
指的就是
that's what I'm talking about the rules
设置所有视图框架的规则
for how to set the frames of all these views.
iOS中有一个很强大的API
There's a really powerful API in iOS for this,
也就是一个程序接口 包含对象
in other word, a program interface with object
布局约束等等全套机制
and its layout constrained and all these mechanisms,
但是绝大部分自动布局的操作
but really, almost all of what we do with autolayout,
都是在Xcode可视化界面中实现的
we do in Xcode, visually,
通常不会使用代码实现
we don't usually go to the code.
如果你要用代码实现
If you're going to the code,
那就是非常高级的布局了
you're doing some pretty advanced layout, okay?
我相信 使用代码
I'm sure it's possible, actually with the code,
可以使用自动布局处理卡牌布局
you could lay your cards out using autolayout,
但在Xcode中可能不行
but Xcode, probably not.
因为全部都是Xcode中的图形化操作
Okay? So since it's all Xcode and it's all graphically,
我就用屏幕截图来讲解
I'm going to do this entire lecture about autolayout
自动布局这部分了
with screen shots, okay?
就直接串讲一遍
And we'll just kind of walk through it,
前面几步我就直接跳过去了
I'm actually going to skip these first few here
我会在示例中演示
because I'll show you that in the demo.
我要新建一个视图
So what I'm gonna do it I'm going to start with a view,
这里的这个控制器的视图
controller's view, right here,
里边有两个Thing
with a couple of things in it.
Thing 1和Thing 2
Thing one and thing two,
苏斯博士抱歉了
with apologies to Dr. Seuss,
Thing 1和Thing 2可以是任意视图
things one and thing two, they can be any kind of view,
这里它们是UILabel
they're UILabels in this case,
但也可以是按钮
but they could be buttons,
可以是自定义视图等等
they could be custom views, whatever,
它们就是Thing 1和Thing 2
they're just thing one and thing two,
我们想让Thing 1和Thing 2
and we want thing one and thing two to
在边界改变时 显示在正确的位置
be in the right place when this bounds changes.
现在如果我让它横屏显示
Okay? So what happens right now,
会发生什么呢
if we go and try and show this in landscape,
我可以运行它
well, I could run this
然后再将模拟器翻转到横屏模式
and then flip the simulator to landscape to see,
但其实还可以将视图控制器场景
but it's actually possible to take your view controller scene,
在Xcode中翻转为横屏模式
and flip it to landscape in Xcode, okay?
有两种方法可以实现
Now there are two ways to do,
一是Xcode中有一个预览器
one is Xcode actually has a previewer,
可以预览
a previewer that will preview
UI在不同情况下的显示效果
what your UI's going to look like
不同的旋转方向 不同的iPhone版本
on different rotations, different iPhones,
甚至iOS7和iOS6的显示效果
even between iOS 7 and iOS 6,
如果你的应用是要兼容两版iOS的话
if you're writing an app that's compatible for both.
另一种方法是直接检查控制器
But another way to do it is just to inspect your controller,
这里我选中了控制器
so here I've selected my controller, right,
蓝色边框表示我已经选中了它
it's got a blue boundary around it and I've selected it,
然后转到属性检查器
and I went to the attributes inspector, you see?
在右上方
Upper right there.
检查它
And I'm inspecting it.
控制器检查器中
And if you look at the inspector for controller,
最上面五项是Simulated Metrics模拟选项
the top five things there are called simulated metrics.
可以在这里设置模拟用户界面
And this is a way to simulate your user interface
选择不同的方向或大小 或者是否有选项卡栏
in different orientations or sizes or with tab bars or not,
通过这样来确认
so that you kind of make sure
UI在自动布局条件下显示正常
your UI is working with autolayout,
这里我们选择切换方向
so we're gonna go and switch the orientation,
选择Orientation方向选项
alright, so I'm picking on this thing orientation,
切换为Landscape横屏模式
and I'm switching it to landscape.
这样做之后
And when I do that,
场景切换为横屏模式 Thing 2没了
my scene changes to landscape and I lost thing two.
Thing 2怎么了
Okay? What happened to thing two?
实际上 Thing 2还在那呢 留在那了
Well, thing two is actually there, I left it there,
变灰了 看到了吗
it's kind of grayed out, you see it?
但是没有显示在屏幕上
But it's not on screen
因为很不幸
because unfortunately in landscape
横屏模式不够长 够不到Thing 2
it doesn't go down far enough to reach thing two.
我把方向切换回去
Okay? So I'm going to switch back.
还要注意 方向选项中
By the way, you notice that the orientation there,
不仅有横屏竖屏 还有一个Inferred推断
there's portrait landscape and there's also inferred.
当修改场景边界时
Okay, for all of these things
对应的这些内容
where you change the bounds of your scene,
Inferred推断表示
inferred means inferred from
从storyboard中进行推断
what's going on in your storyboard.
如果这个场景是在导航控制器中
So this's the thing that makes a bar come across the top
它就会在顶部添加一条导航栏
if this scene is in a navigation controller,
如果是一个选项卡栏控制器
or a bar across the bottom
就在底部添加一条选项卡栏
if this scene is a tab bar controller, okay?
竖屏是默认的推断方向
Portrait is the default inferred orientation,
所以如果你选择推断选项
so if you pick inferred,
就像其他选项选择推断一样
just like you pick inferred for the other things,
它会推断你指的是竖屏
it will infer that you mean portrait.
如果你选择竖屏...
So whether you say portrait landscape,
竖屏和推断选项的方向一样的
portrait or inferred are the same for orientation.
横屏就代表横屏
Landscape means landscape.
我们再将方向设回为推断或竖屏
So let's go back to inferred, or to portrait.
Thing 2又回来了
We get thing two back.
Thing 2哪都没去
Okay, thing two didn't go anywhere,
它之前还在那 只不过不显示在屏幕上了
it was there before, it just wasn't on screen.
我想将Thing 1和Thing 2放在更合适的位置上
So, I want to put thing one and thing two in better places.
它们现在是随机放置的
They're kind of in random places,
我想将它们放在某个特定位置
I want to put them in places
这样就可以为它们的显示位置设定规则了
where I can have a rule that says where they are,
我要做的是
and then what I'm going to do is
将Thing 1放到左上角
I'm gonna put thing one in the upper left corner
将Thing 2放到右下角
and I'm gonna put thing two in the lower right corner,
让Thing 1和Thing2
and I always want thing one and thing two
始终位于这两个角上
to stay in those corners,
无论这两个角的位置如何移动
no matter where those corners move.
如果转为横屏模式 下角上移
Okay? If those corners move up in the landscape
或者因为iPhone版本不同 下角下移
or down because it's an iPhone, the tall iPhone,
比如更长的iPhone 5等等
like an iPhone 5, or up, or whatever,
我想让这两个Thing始终显示在两个角上
I want those things to stick to their corners,
所以我要的规则就是始终显示在两个角上
so the rules I want is stick in the corners, okay,
我要演示三种设置规则的方法
I'm gonna show you three ways to set rules,
这节课上会讲三种不同的方法
over the course of this lecture, three different ways.
第一种方法 大家已经用过了
The first way, you have already been doing.
无意间用过了 也不是完全无意
Unwittingly, well, not really unwittingly
因为是我告诉大家这样做的
because I've been telling you to do it,
就是使用蓝色辅助线
which is to use those blue guidelines, okay?
当拖出对象时
When you drag things around
借助蓝线将其放置到特定位置
and you let the blue guidelines snap to certain locations,
就是告诉了Xcode你想要怎样
you're basically telling Xcode what you want.
当我将Thing 1拖到左上角时
So when I drag thing one up into this upper left-hand corner
出现这两条蓝线
and these two blue lines appear,
就是告诉Xcode
it's really telling Xcode, yeah,
我想让它跟着这两条线
I want it to be stuck to this line and stuck to this line,
也就是左上角
in other words, upper left there.
Thing 2也是一样的
And same thing when I do that for thing two.
我告诉了Xcode要怎样处理
Okay? I'm kind of telling Xcode.
但是我这样拖动放置之后
But if I drag these two things then, right,
再次切换至横屏模式
and then I switch over to landscape again,
Thing 2依旧无法显示出来
I still don't get thing two.
为什么不行呢 我用了蓝线
Why not? Okay, I did the blue lines,
为什么不能用呢
how come it doesn't work?
答案是 借助蓝线可以告诉Xcode
And the answer is, all the blue lines are
你想要什么
is telling Xcode what you intend.
你还得要求Xcode
You still have to ask Xcode,
为我执行这些规则 这些约束
make those rules for me, make those constraints.
我们回到竖屏方向
Okay? So let's go back to, to the portrait orientation,
实现方法是
and the way you do that,
通过底部的这些小按钮
is the little buttons at the bottom,
看到底部的按钮了吗
you see these buttons at the bottom,
我点击了一个
those, here I'll click on one.
它们都与自动布局有关
Those all have to do with autolayout, okay?
表示你要如何布局视图
And how you're going to layout the view.
这个像钛战机的按钮
And this one, that looked kind of like a TIE fighter,
星球大战里面的钛战机
a Star Wars TIE fighter there,
是用于重置的
that one is kind of for resetting,
清除整个视图的约束
clearing constraints for the entire view,
或是你选中的
okay, or for a specific view or number of views
某个或某些视图的约束
that you have selected.
菜单底部是整个视图
So the bottom part of this menu is the entire view,
顶部也是一样的
the top part is the same things,
但针对的是某些选定视图
but for specific clicked on views, okay?
我们会讲讲其中几个
So, we'll go through a few of these things,
有一个很酷 就是这个重置为建议约束
but a really cool one is reset to suggested constraints, okay?
建议约束代表
Suggested constraints means Xcode is going to suggest
Xcode会向你推荐最好的约束 最好的规则
to you the best constraints, the best rules,
而且只有在你使用了蓝色辅助线的条件下
and it's only going to be very good at that
才会好用
if you use the blue guidelines.
因为如果你没有使用蓝色辅助线
Because if you don't use the blue guidelines,
它就不知道要建议什么
it doesn't really know what to suggest.
它会推荐一些约束
It'll suggest something,
但并不好用 我们会看到
but it's not gonna be good as we'll see.
但在这个例子中
But in this case,
因为Thing 1和Thing 2都明确使用了蓝色辅助线
since both thing one and thing two clearly have blue guidelines
来表示它们的位置
to say where they want to be,
这里我们使用重置为建议约束
when we do reset to suggested constraints,
就可以起作用了
it's going to work.
什么都没有发生
Now, nothing appears to happen, right?
我设置了重置为建议约束 什么都没发生
I did reset suggest content and nothing happened.
但确实有变化
But something did happen,
我们可以点击Thing 1
and we can see that by clicking on thing one
然后转到尺寸检查器
and going over to the size inspector.
右边检查器这里 我切换到了尺寸检查器
Okay, so in the inspector there, I've switched over to size,
点击那个像尺子一样的图标
that thing looks kind of like a ruler,
尺寸检查器中可以看到
and size inspector has, you know,
当前框架的位置等等
where the current frame is and all that,
但在底部 看到Constraints约束这部分了吗
but at the bottom, do you see where it says constraints?
有两个约束
And I have two constraints.
第一个是Leading Space前置间距
My leading space, okay,
这里用前置间距而不是左间距
the reason that says leading space instead of left space
是因为在某些语言中 文字是从右边开始的
is because some languages, leading is on the right.
希伯来语等语言是从右向左的
Okay? So Hebrew, a language like that, it's on the right
所以你或许想让你的整个用户界面
so you might want your entire user interface
都从右边开始
oriented towards coming from the right, okay,
而不是从左边开始
instead of coming from the left,
因为你的文字是从右向左的
because all your text is going to be going that way,
所以整个用户界面最好也是这个方向的
so you might want all your user interface to flow from that way.
前置指的就是文字开始的方向
So anyway, so leading means whichever leading you're talking about,
我想让前置间距与父视图绑定
and I want the leading space to be tied to my superview,
与父视图的边缘
the edge of my superview,
间距为某个固定值 这个值是默认的
by some fixed amount, and that fixed amount is default.
Default
Default. Okay?
不是个魔术数字 是由系统决定的
It's not a magic number, its default, it's by the system,
系统决定默认值是多少
the system decides what that default amount is.
还可以看到 上间距也和父视图的上边缘绑定
And then you can see my top space is also tied
间距为默认值Default
to my superview's top edge with the default space.
这两个约束决定了
So those two constraints determine exactly
Thing 1的准确位置
where thing one's going to be.
Thing 1的大小是怎样的呢
Now what about thing one's size.
Thing 1会始终保持
Okay? Is thing one always going
当前宽度吗
to be exactly the width it is right now?
Thing 1和所有标签及按钮一样
No. Thing one, like all labels and buttons,
有一个内置大小
it has what's called an intrinsic size.
也就是它的文本需要的尺寸
Okay? That's the size that its text demands that it be.
这是可以修改的
And that could change.
如果你修改了Thing 1的文字 它就会变宽
If you change the text in thing one, it needs to be wider
如果你减少了文字 它就会缩短
or it could be shorter if you change it to something shorter.
所以它的尺寸会随着文本的变化而变化
And so, it will change its size as you change its text.
因为你没有向其添加尺寸约束
Okay? Because you haven't put a constraint on its size.
如果你增加了一个尺寸约束
If you put a constraint on its size,
它就会始终保持那个大小 这样不好
it would then be stuck to that size and that is bad.
通常情况下 我们不会为具有内置大小的控件
We do not put size constraints, generally,
设置尺寸约束 比如标签和按钮
on intrinsically sizable items like labels and buttons,
我会在示例中演示
and I'm going to show you, hopefully,
为什么这样不好 希望有时间演示
if we have time in the demo, why that's bad, okay?
总之 Thing 1只有这两个约束
So anyway, thing one only has those two constraints,
但这两个约束完全可以决定Thing 1的位置
but those two constraints completely determine thing one's location
无论父视图是怎样的
no matter what the superview does.
Thing 2也是一样的
Same thing with thing two,
可以设置下间距和后置间距
bottom space and the trailing space.
现在我们来看一下横屏模式
Okay? So now let's go look in landscape.
我要切换到横屏 看看效果如何
I'm going to switch over to landscape and see what happens.
可以看到 Thing 2始终显示在右下角
And you can see, thing two sticks to that corner,
就是我们想要的效果
kind of exactly what we want.
这是因为Thing 2的位置
Alright? And that's because thing two's position
现在完全由那些规则决定
is totally determined by those rules now, okay?
再回到竖屏
Okay, so let's go back to portrait.
我要再加一个Bad Thing
So, I'm going to put a bad thing in there, okay?
这个Bad Thing会演示可能会发生的不好的事情
So this bad thing is going to show bad things that can happen,
我想将Bad Thing放到中间
and I tried to put bad thing in the middle,
但是我没用蓝色辅助线
but I didn't use the blue guidelines.
这其实挺难做到的 但是我做到了
That's actually difficult to do, but I did.
我增加了一个Bad Thing
Okay, I put a bad thing in.
而且这个Bad Thing的尺寸太大了
Also, you know, this bad thing size, it's too big for itself,
不需要那么大
it really doesn't want to be that big,
如果用内置大小的话 会小得多
it could be a lot smaller if it was just an intrinsic size.
我只是将它拖出来 移动缩放控点
So, I just dragged it out and moved the sizing handles.
它没有约束 因为我刚把它拖出来
It has no constraints, because I just dragged it out, okay?
看右边的尺寸检查器 写着无约束
See how its size inspector there says no constraints, right?
没有约束
You have no constraints.
如果我向Xcode请求
So, what happens if I try to ask Xcode,
请为Bad Thing提供一些建议约束 会怎样
please give me some suggested constraints for bad thing.
要记得 拖放Bad Thing时
Remember, I didn't use the blue guidelines
我没有使用蓝色辅助线
when I dragged bad thing out.
还要注意 我使用的是菜单的上半部分
And notice, also, I'm using the top half of that menu
是针对Bad Thing的
which is just, just for bad thing.
并没有重置Thing 1和Thing 2
Okay? I'm not resetting thing one and thing two,
但我可以一直重置Thing 1和Thing2
although I could reset thing one and thing two all day long,
因为它们始终会被重置为合适约束
because they're always gonna reset to the proper constraints
因为我对它们使用了建议约束
because I'm using the suggested constraints for them.
这里我就只重置Bad Thing的约束
But anyway, so I'm just gonna reset bad things constraints
出来了
and, boom!
Xcode尽力了 这很难
Xcode gives it the old college try, but it's hard, okay?
实际上 看一下它给出的
And, in fact, look at the constraints
这些约束
it came up with there.
高度为62 前置间距为89 后置间距为68
Height equals 62, leading space equals 89, trailing space 68,
换句话说 这些都是魔术数字
in other words, these are all magic numbers.
这很糟糕 是很差的约束条件
Okay? This is horrible, these are terrible constraints.
带有魔术数字的约束几乎都很糟糕
Constraints with magic numbers are almost always bad.
少数情况下可以使用
There's a few cases where they're okay,
但通常都很糟糕
but it's almost always bad,
如果我切换到横屏模式
and, in fact, if I go and try to switch to landscape,
这些数字都不变
all of those number stay exactly the same, okay?
上边距依旧为198
It stays 198 pixels from the top,
左边距也不变
and whatever it was from the left,
完全不是我想要的效果
it's totally not what I want.
我是要将Bad Thing放在中间
Okay? I tried to put bad thing in the middle.
我想让它始终显示在中间
I want it to stay in the middle,
现在离中间还差得远呢
that's not even close to being in the middle.
所以如果你不使用蓝色辅助线
So suggested constraints aren't gonna work
建议约束就不会起作用
if you don't use the blue guidelines
因为它不确定你想要什么效果
because it's not really sure what you want.
我们删掉这些约束
Okay? So, so let's get rid of these constraints.
方法是回到刚才那个菜单
I'm going to go back to that same menu
选择另外一项 也就是Clear Constraints清除约束
and pick a different item, which is clear constraints,
这样就清除了全部约束
and that clears all the constraints,
回到最初状态
and goes back to this thing.
还要注意 全部约束都会被绘制出来
Notice, by the way, all the constraints draw,
看到蓝线了吗
you see the blue bars?
每个约束都会被绘制出来
See them? Every single constraint is drawn.
它们不仅会被绘制出来
And not only does it draw those constraints,
你还可以点击它们 然后进行编辑
you can click on them, and edit them.
很多约束都有属性
A lot of the constraints have attributes,
很可惜 今天我没时间讲了
which I'm not gonna have time to talk about today, unfortunately,
这些约束是storyboard的
but those constraints are first-class objects
一类对象
inside of your, your storyboard.
好的 我们清除掉这些约束
Alright. So we're gonna clear those out of there.
我们换一种方法来添加约束
And let's put in some constraints in a different way.
这是添加约束的第二种方法
So this is way number two to add constraints.
第一种方法是使用蓝色辅助线 然后选择建议约束
And way number one was use blue guidelines and say suggested.
这是添加约束的第一种方法
That's way number one to put constraints on.
第二种方法是
Number two is you can use
可以使用底部的这些按钮
some of these other buttons at the bottom.
比如这个按钮就是用来设置对齐的
Like this particular button here for aligning things.
看这个菜单
So if you look in this,
上面有很多对齐选项
there's a lot of choices of how to align things,
如果我选择多个视图
if I selected multiple views,
那么上部的这些选项
then all of those things at the top,
比如前边缘 后边缘 上边缘
like leading edges, trailing edges, top edges,
我可以选择它们
I'd be able to pick those
对齐视图的前边缘或者后边缘等等
and I could line up the leading edges or trailing edges
让它们对齐
or whatever, of views, make them line up.
就是对齐
Okay? It's just alignment things,
和绘图程序等是一样的
just like if you're in some drawing program or something.
我要选择底下的两个
I'm gonna pick the bottom two, which lines this thing up
在父视图中水平居中对齐
with the horizontal center in the superview.
所以它会在父视图中居中
So it's gonna be centered in my superview,
水平居中 垂直居中
both horizontally and vertically,
所以我要在这里增加两个约束
so I'm going to add two constraints here,
一个是水平约束 一个是垂直约束
one for horizontal, one for vertical.
还可以指定中心的偏移量
And I can also specify an offset from the center,
就是现在选中的那个0的含义
that's what that zero is right there that's selected,
我要让它显示在正中心
but I'm going to have the exact in the center,
所以这里设为0
so I'm going to say zero.
还有一个Update Frames更新框架
And there's also update frames,
看到底部的Update Frames了吗
you see the update frames at the bottom there
就在"添加两条约束"上面
right above where it says add two constraints.
可以在这里的弹出菜单中设置
That popup, you can go in there and say,
当添加约束时
and when you add these constraints,
移动视图以匹配这些约束
move my view to fit those constraints,
但这里我就不设置了
but I'm not going to set that
因为我想为大家演示一下
because I want to show you what happens
如果这里不设置会怎样
if you don't do that, okay?
我们添加这两个约束
So let's add these two constraints,
水平和垂直居中
horizontal and vertical centering.
它们显示出来了
Okay. There they are.
在父视图中X轴居中
You see them, align center X to superview,
在父视图中Y轴居中 很好
align center Y to superview, awesome.
可以看到这两个约束
You can see them, they're there.
注意 它们是黄色的
Notice that they're yellow.
黄色代表警告
Okay, yellow is like a warning, okay?
出现黄色不是什么好事
Yellow is not good.
蓝色很好 黄色不是那么好 红色很糟糕
Blue is good, yellow not so good, red is really bad.
有时约束会显示为红色
Okay? Sometimes your constraints will be red,
那就是发生冲突了
that's if they conflict.
有两个约束是完全相反的
You got two constraints sitting, doing opposite things.
我们会讲到如何解决这个问题
And we'll talk about how we resolve all this.
这里是黄色的
So it's yellow.
如果仔细看
Also, if you look really closely,
可以看到有一个虚线框
you see there's a dashed box, kind of right,
穿过Bad Thing
it goes right through the word bad over to the thing,
看到了吗
you see it right there,
在大矩形中的虚线框
dashed box inside of the bigger box?
大家能看清这个虚线框吗
That dashed box, I don't know how well you can see that there,
能看清 这个虚线框代表
yeah you can see it, that dashed box is
约束条件认为的该控件的所在位置
where you constraints say this thing should be.
换句话说就是 如果只看约束
Okay? In other words, if you just looked at your constraints,
Bad Thing应该在哪
where should bad thing be?
它应该显示在那个小虚线框中
Well, it should be in that little dashed box,
因为我们刚才没有勾选底部的
but since we didn't click that thing at the bottom there
将框架更新至约束位置
that said update my frame to where my constraints are
Bad Thing就没有移动
it didn't do it.
所以Bad Thing还在原来的位置
So bad thing is still where it was,
这也就是为什么它们是黄色的原因
and that's why these are yellow.
如何知道约束变为黄色的原因呢
Okay? How can I know why my constraints are yellow?
一个地方就是右上角的小三角形那里
Well, one place is that little triangle in the upper corner,
就是看应用中其他警告的
the normal triangle where you would look at
三角形那里
any other warning in your app,
这里的警告是
and you can see this
Bad Thing的框架在运行时会不同
as the frame for bad thing will be different at run time.
因为在运行时
That's because at run time
约束会被应用
the constraints are going to be applied
它就会被移动到那个小虚线框中
and it's gonna be moved into that little dashed box.
如果约束为黄色
Okay? Another place you can see these warnings,
还有一个地方可以查看警告 就是在文档大纲中
if you're constraints are yellow is in the document outline.
我们在课上还没有机会
Now we have not had a chance
讲到文档大纲
to talk about the document outline in this class,
但其实也没什么要讲的
but there's not really a lot to say about
除了一点 就是它很棒 是什么呢
except for that it's really great and what is it?
是以大纲的形式列出storyboard中
It's every single object in your storyboard
每一个对象
that matters in an outline form.
全部视图 全部手势
Okay? So that's all your views, all your gestures,
全部约束 布局向导
all your constraints, things like layout guides,
我们还没有机会讲呢
which we're really not getting a chance to talk about,
也和自动布局系统有关
but has to do with auto layout system, as well.
这些都列在大纲中
Those are all listed in this outline,
特别棒的一点是 你可以通过点击选中它们
and what's really cool is you can click on them to select.
因为有时视图中对象很多
Because sometimes your view's very crowded
很难通过点击选择你想要的对象
and it's hard to click on the thing you want
即便使用了我教大家的Control Shift技巧也一样
even using the control shift trick that I showed you,
你还可以从这里进行control拖拽
and also you can control drag from them.
可以从一个手势进行control拖拽
Okay? You can control drag from a gesture,
可以从一个视图进行control拖拽
you control drag from a view.
在这里进行control拖拽非常方便
It's a really great place to control drag things from, okay?
入门指导第一条
That's pro-tip number one.
从文档大纲中进行control拖拽
Drag, control drag from document outline.
文档大纲还可以显示出
The document online, also,
自动布局的全部问题
will show you all the problems with your autolayout
看到上面那个小黄色圆形图标了吗
and you see the tiny, little, yellow circle up there
在文档大纲顶部
where it says view controller scene
视图控制器场景右侧
at the top of the document outline
那里有一个小的黄色圆形图标
and then there's that little yellow circle,
点击它
I'm going to click on that circle,
就会显示出这个控制器中 这个场景中
and it's going to show me all the autolayout problems
自动布局的全部问题
in this controller, in this scene.
可以看到有Bad Thing
And you can see the bad thing,
它预期框架是上面的值 实际框架是不同的
it expects a certain frame and the actual frame is different.
可以看到右边有一个小三角形
And you see the little triangle there,
如果点击它 就会提供...
if I click on that triangle, it will offer me to,
会为我提供问题的解决方案
offer to solve the problem for me.
我如何才能解决这个问题呢
Okay? Now, how can I solve the problem?
有几种解决方法
Well, there's a number of ways it could solve the problem.
可以将Bad Thing的框架
It could change the frame of bad thing
修改为约束的值
to be what the constraints say,
这就是Update Frame更新框架的作用
that's what update frame is.
还可以修改约束
It could update the constraints instead of being
不再是我刚才设置的水平垂直居中
the vertical and horizontal center that I just set it to,
可以将其设回为
it could set them back to being something that would make,
某个能让Bad Thing框架使用的约束
you know, the bad things frame work,
还可以将其设为建议约束
or it could try to set it to the suggested constraints,
我们已经知道这行不通了
which we already know don't work.
所以在这个例子中 我们需要的当然是更新框架
So we definitely want update frame in this case.
我们喜欢我们的约束
We know we like our constraints,
也就是水平垂直居中
that's the horizontal, vertical centering.
所以我们要选择这一项
So we're going to pick that.
选择Update Frame选项
So I'm going to leave update frame suggested
点击Fix Misplacement修复错位
and click where it says fix misplacement,
看看Bad Thing会怎样
and watch what's going to happen to bad thing.
它移动了 现在没有黄色警告了
It moved. Okay, now, everything is no longer yellow,
Bad Thing框架被设置为了
bad things frame has been set
约束要求的值
to what the constraints demand of it. Okay?
我点击了返回 回到文档大纲中
And I just hit back to go back to, in the document online.
现在我们回到横屏模式
So now let's go look in landscape
看看Bad Thing会怎样
and see what happens to bad thing.
它始终显示在中间
It stays centered.
Bad Thing始终很好地显示在中间
Okay? Bad thing properly stays centered,
因为它只有一条规则
because the only rules it has,
就是让它显示在中间
is for it to be in the center.
好了 回到这里
Okay? Alright, so back here.
我刚才说过了
Okay. You can also click on, I told you,
你还可以点击这些约束
you could click on these constraints.
这里我点击了垂直约束
So here I clicked on the vertical constraint there,
我刚点了它
you can see, I just clicked on it,
可以看到 它被突出显示出来了
and you see how it's kind of highlighted.
还要注意 属性检查器
Also notice that the attribute inspector started being an inspector
现在检查的是X轴居中约束
that's inspecting the center X alignment constraint.
有很多关于约束的选项
Okay? And there's a lot of things
可以在这里进行设置
you can set about constraints.
注意这里有一个Priority优先级选项
Notice there's a priority there,
因为在复杂布局中可能会有两个约束
because you might have two constraints in a complicated layout,
只会出现于复杂布局的情况
only complicated ones,
你的约束之间可能会有冲突
you might have conflicting constraints.
你想让某个控件显示在另一个控件的下面
You want something to be underneath something else,
但你还想让它显示在屏幕的中间
but you want it to try and be in the middle of the screen,
但如果屏幕变得很小
but if the screen gets really small,
这时你就想将它移出来
then you want it to just move down
不被上面的控件遮挡
out of the way of the thing on top,
可以为这种冲突约束设置优先级
those kind of conflicting constraints you can set priorities,
哪个更重要呢
to say which is more important?
在中间显示
Is it more important to be in the middle
还是在另一个视图下面更加重要
or is it more important to be underneath this other view?
明白我的意思吗
You see what I'm saying?
优先级范围可以是1到1000
So you can set your priorities between zero and a thousand,
1000个控件可以有各自不同的优先级
so you, up to thousand items could have varying priorities
通常情况下  整个应用中
and generally you're gonna only use two or three
只会用到两三个不同的优先级
different priorities in your entire application, but--
选中约束时 还可以做一件事情
anyway, the other thing you can do
就是点击删除键
when you have this selected is hit delete.
删除选中的约束
And that deletes that constraint.
可以看到 这时Bad Thing
And now you can see the bad thing
只有这个Y轴居中约束
only has this center Y constraint.
现在就没有指定它的水平位置了
So it no longer specifies where it is horizontally,
这真的很糟糕
and that is really bad
现在再看文档大纲
and now if you look at the document outline,
右上不仅出现了圆形图标 它还是红色的
I not only have a little dot up there, but its red.
如果这里有一个不太好的约束
Okay? And if I had a constraint that was bad here,
问题是缺少约束
the problem is I have a lack of constraint,
没有足够的约束
I don't have enough constraints
指定Bad Thing的水平位置
to specify where bad thing is horizontally,
但如果有两个约束冲突了 就会是红色的
but if I had two that conflicted, they would be red.
明白吗
Okay?
显示在屏幕上的约束线会是红色的
The constraint, the lines on screen would be red
大纲右上角会出现红色的圆形图标
and I would have this little red circle.
点击文档大纲中的红色圆形图标
So let's click on that red circle in the document outline
这里说它缺失约束
and here it's saying missing constraints, okay,
Bad Thing需要X轴位置的约束
bad thing needs constraints for X position, it's saying,
确实需要
which it does.
不然它怎么知道要把Bad Thing放在哪里呢
Because how else is it gonna know where to put X, bad thing,
没有规则说明它应该放在哪里
there's nothing that says where to put it
因为我删掉了
because I took that constraint
那个要求它显示在中间的约束
that was telling it to be in the middle away.
我们点击红色圆形图标
So let's click on that red thing,
点击之后 系统会提供解决方案
and when we do, it's going to offer to fix that.
它说 让我试着加一个缺失的约束
And it says let me try and add a missing constraint,
它会尽己所能
and it's going to do the best it can
添加一个或多个约束
to add a constraint or a number of constraints
让它至少不缺少约束
to make it so that at least there's not a missing constraint.
可能并不是你想要的约束
This might not be the constraint you want, but, you know,
很可能就是建议约束
it's probably gonna be mostly suggested constraints,
但是添加这个约束之后
but it's gonna be some kind of constraint so that there--
该元素的位置和大小
so the position of this thing, and its size,
就能够完全确定了
are completely specified.
在这个例子中
So, in this case,
因为我们已经用蓝线将其居中对齐
since we already blue guidelined this thing to the middle,
我们知道它就在正中
and we know it's exactly in the middle,
当我们点击增加缺失约束时
when we hit add missing constraints,
它会把那个约束再加回来
it's going to put that thing back.
也不是恢复之前那个约束
Okay? Now it's not putting it back
因为系统知道我删掉了它
because it knows I deleted it,
只不过它认为这是最适合这里的约束
it's just thinking that's the best constraint that goes here.
它知道这个元素在正中间
Because it knows this thing is dead center,
它就会想 正中间 好吧
so it's like, hmm, dead center thing,
我也许应该添加一个这样的约束
I'm probably going to do that.
系统真的很聪明
So it's really smart
知道要增加哪个缺失约束
about what missing constraints it will put in there.
大多数情况下都会用建议约束
Mostly it's going to use suggested constraints,
但是它很聪明 并不会只用建议约束
but it's even smarter than just the suggested system.
现在自动布局就没有问题了
Okay? So now we have no autolayout issues,
Bad Thing又位于很好的位置了
we're back to having bad thing in a good spot.
如果我不想让Bad Thing显示在中间了呢
Now what if I decided I don't want bad thing in the middle,
我想让Bad Thing始终显示在
I want bad thing to be stacked
Thing 2的上面
on top of thing two all the time?
我只要拾取Bad Thing 向下拖动
So I just pick up bad thing and drag it down,
可以选择是否使用蓝色辅助线 这里要用
I'll use the blue guidelines or not, but I'm using the--
将它拖动到那里 然后松开鼠标
I'm just going to drag it down there and I drop it.
发生了什么
And what happens?
又一次出现了黄色辅助线
Well, I get the yellow guidelines again,
因为Bad Thing又被放到了错误的位置
because bad thing, once again, is misplaced.
这是因为当你将控件拖动到新位置时
That's because when you drag things to new positions,
并不会改变其约束
it does not change the constraints.
这一点很重要 需要大家理解
That's important to understand.
将控件拖至新位置时
When you drag things somewhere new,
约束不变
the constraints stay the same.
Bad Thing的约束
So bad thing's constraints are still
依旧是水平垂直居中
align center X and align Y, you see?
看到了吗
See them right there?
这样不好
And that's no good.
我们能做什么呢
So, what can we do about that?
我们也许想要删掉这些约束
Well, we probably want to delete these constraints,
因为它们不再适用了
because they no longer apply,
我演示了使用清除约束删掉它们的方法
and I showed you how to delete them by doing clear constraints,
我还讲了如何选中它们
and I told you how to delete them
然后点击删除的方法
by clicking on them and hit delete.
还有一种删除方法
Here's another way to delete them,
看到那个小齿轮了吗
you see the little cog, right there,
在Y轴居中和X轴居中约束线上
where it says align center Y and align center X,
有一个小齿轮
there's a little cog,
如果点击它 会出现一个小菜单
if you click on that, there's a little menu,
你可以对它进行编辑
you can edit it,
和属性检查器是完全一样的
which is exactly the same as attributes inspector on it,
你还可以选择删除它
or you can delete it.
我要删除这两个约束
So I'll delete that one and I'll delete that one.
这样我就删掉了这些约束
So now I got rid of those constraints,
Bad Thing又回到了没有约束的状态
bad things back to having no constraints.
我这样做只是为了给大家演示
I just did that because I wanted to show you
有多种删除方法
that there's multiple ways to get at this thing.
还可以在文档大纲中选中它们
You can also delete them by selecting them
然后点击删除
in the document outline and hitting delete. Okay?
现在Bad Thing显示在那里
So now I have bad thing, but where it is there,
但它并没有和Thing 2绑定
it's not tied to thing two.
如果现在切换为横屏模式
If I were to go landscape right now,
它不会随着Thing 2移动
it would not stick with thing two
因为没有约束将其与Thing 2绑定
because there's no constraint that ties it to thing two.
那我们就添加一个约束
Okay? So, let's put a constraint.
这是第三种方法
Here's way number three, okay,
大家还记得第一种方法是什么吗
do you remember what ways number one are?
第一种方法是使用蓝色辅助线 选择建议约束
Number one is blue guideline suggested constraint,
这是第一种方法 对吧
that's way number one, alright?
大家还记得吗
Everybody got that?
第二种方法是使用底部的菜单按钮
Number two is to use the little menu things at the bottom.
点击按钮 弹出菜单 输入数值
Click, bring up the little thing, type in,
选择水平约束等等 点击你需要的约束
click horizontal, whatever, click the things that you want.
第三种方法是使用control拖拽
Way number three is to control drag, control drag,
和添加输出口的操作是一样的
just like you're making an outlet,
在两个目标对象之间进行拖拽
between two items that you want
添加约束关系
to have some sort of constrained relationship.
我要从Bad Thing按住control键拖拽到Thing 2
So I'm gonna control drag from bad thing to thing two.
这样做之后 会弹出一个黑色菜单
Okay? And when I do, I get a little black box
类似于添加输出口的菜单
just like if I was making an outlet,
但是这里要选择的是
but this time it's saying what do you want to tie
要怎样绑定两个对象
between these two items?
你想让这两个对象间的什么值固定
What do you want to be fixed between these two?
实际上 你可以按住shift键进行多选
So, you can actually select multiple of these using shift,
底下提示的就是这个
that's what it says at the bottom there,
按住shift键选择多项
hold shift to select multiple.
我要选择垂直间距
So I'm going to pick the vertical spacing,
我想让Bad Thing以固定的垂直间距
I want bad thing to always be a fixed vertical space
始终显示在Thing 2的上方
above thing two,
我还要选择右边缘
and I'm also gonna pick right edge, okay?
这里说的是左边缘和右边缘
And this is saying left and right,
实际上是前边缘和后边缘
but it's really trailing and leading,
只不过系统现在知道你的左右方向
it just right now it knows which is your left and right
用右边缘是为了更方便你
so it's saying right to be nice to you.
所以我要选择垂直间距
So I'm gonna pick both vertical spacing
和右边缘这两项
and the right edges, okay?
这样做之后 可以看到添加了两个约束
When I do that, you can see I get two constraints.
可以在屏幕上看到 IB上出现了两条蓝线
You can see them on screen, two little blue lines in the IB,
在Bad Thing和Thing 2之间
between bad thing and thing two,
代表二者右边缘对齐
that is lining up the right edges
将二者间距设为固定的默认值
and fixing the space between them to the default space.
这是因为我用了蓝色辅助线
Okay, that's because I used the blue guidelines.
如果我没用蓝色辅助线
If I hadn't used the blue guidelines
而是将Bad Thing放在Thing 2上面40像素处
and had put bad thing, you know, 40 pixels above,
那么间距就固定为40像素
then it would have fixed it to 40 pixels,
但我们会在约束中看到40
but we would have seen in the constraints 40,
约束中有魔术数字
and we said a magic number is in constraints,
我们最好改一下
we better fix that.
你可以编辑约束
Okay? Which you could do by editing the constraint and just--
会有一个按钮
there's a button actually
可以将其设为默认值
that says put it, make it the default.
明白吗
Alright?
现在我将这两个控件这样绑定起来了
So now I have these two things tied in that way,
这些约束
again, this is totally enough
可以准确指定它们的位置
to specify all of their positions exactly,
因为Thing 2绑定在了右下角
because thing two is tied to the corner
Bad Thing与Thing 2右边缘对齐
and bad thing is tied to the right edge
绑定在它的上方
and just above thing two.
如果我们再转为横屏模式
So, if we go to landscape again,
Bad Thing会始终和Thing 2保持这个距离
bad thing will always stay that distance
且始终与Thing 2右边缘对齐
and always to the right edge of thing two.
这是吸附对象的第三种方法
Okay? So that's way number three to attach things
就是在二者之间进行control拖拽
is to control drag between them
可以在两个控件 两个视图之间进行control拖拽
and you control drag between items, between views,
还可以从某个视图向其父视图进行control拖拽
you can also control drag from a view to its superview,
就是我现在做的这个操作
that's what I'm doing here.
从Bad Thing拖拽到它的父视图
Bad thing to its superview
会弹出另外一组选项
and you'll get a different set of options,
比如容器内水平垂直居中
like horizontal and vertical container.
还可以向自己进行control拖拽
Or you could also control drag to yourself.
为什么要向自己进行control拖拽呢
Okay? Why would you ever control drag to yourself?
我有一个Bad Thing
I have a bad thing,
为什么要从Bad Thing control拖拽到它自己呢
why would I control drag bad thing to itself?
这样弹出的选项是
Well, then I'll get the option to do things
将Bad Thing的宽度设为固定值
like fix bad thing's width, okay?
如果你要处理的是按钮或标签这种有内置大小的元素
Which I told you was bad anytime you have a button or a label
我说了这样处理很不好
or anything that has, you know, an intrinsic size like that.
如果附近有可以依附的对象的话
It'll also, if there's some nearby thing it could do,
还会有将容器的后置间距设为固定值等选项
like fix the trailing space to its container,
它也可以为你完成这类操作
it could do that for you too,
反正是可以向自己进行control拖拽的
but you can control drag to yourself too,
听起来很疯狂 但是你们会习惯的
which sounds crazy, but you'll get used to doing that.
所以control是设置约束的第三种方法
So control drag is way number three to set up constraints.
这套系统中有很多内容
Okay? So, there is a lot to this system.
我只是尽可能多地为大家演示
I've just tried to kind of show you
到哪里查看各种内容
where to look for everything.
如何点击 如何检查
How to click on things, where to inspect them,
怎样查看约束
where to see the constraints,
怎样在文档大纲中解决问题
how to go on the document outline to resolve problems,
无论警告是红色的还是黄色的
whether they'd be red or yellow,
要想将全部可设的
it would take me many lectures
不同的约束都讲一遍
to cover all the different kinds of constraints
要很多节课才能讲完
that you can set up, and--
比如说
you know, for example,
看到右侧检查器中
do you see on the, in the inspector there
有一项是Content Hugging Priority
where it says content hugging priority,
还有一个Content Compression Resistance Priority
and content compression resistance priority?
"拥抱"优先级[压缩优先级]
That hugging priority,
并不是因为视图们互相喜欢
that's not because these views love each other,
有时确实是的
but sometimes they do,
但是大部分情况下 用压缩优先级
but mostly the hugging priority is
是因为有时有些视图
because you have sometimes views
会共享某个水平或垂直的空间
that are sharing some horizontal or vertical space.
当它们共享空间时
And when they share,
有的视图会被减小空间
and that space gets removed from them, or gets taken away,
有的会被增加空间
or they get more space added to them,
系统需要知道
they need to know
哪个视图最想保持自己的大小
which of those views wants to keep its size the most
哪个想要得到更多的空间
and which of them wants to get extra,
哪一个视图愿意被压缩
and which is willing to be compressed
哪一个不愿意被压缩
and which is not willing to get compressed,
所以就要用到内容抗压缩优先级
thus you have compression resistance priority
和内容压缩优先级
and content hugging priority. Okay?
关于这部分 我要讲的就是这些
So, that's as much as I'm going to say about those,
如果大家要用的话 要自己查阅文档
you've got to read up on those if you're gonna do that.
在作业中
You don't need, you're not gonna be building UIs,
大家应该不用构建这样的UI
I don't think, like that in your homework,
如果要的话 大家就自行查看内容压缩优先级
if you are, more power to you to go look up content hugging
和内容抗压缩优先级的内容
and content compression resistances.
最后还剩一个选项就是Intrinsic Size内置大小
Okay? The last thing there you see is intrinsic size.
很多iOS对象都有内置大小
Again, a bunch of iOS things have an intrinsic size,
比如标签和按钮
like labels and buttons,
但其实你可以对自定义视图进行设置
but you could actually have your own custom views,
这也不是作业的要求
again, not for your homework,
你可以让自定义视图
you could have your own custom views
具有内置大小
that have their own intrinsic size,
只要实现一个小API
they just have to implement a little API
用来返回它们的内置大小
that reports their intrinsic size,
在弹出的菜单上
and that little popup there
可以告诉Xcode如何处理自定义视图
let you tell Xcode how to handle that,
因为它只知道
because it doesn't really know
系统对象的处理方法
how to handle that for non system objects,
比如标签和按钮
like labels and buttons.
明白了吗
Okay?
我要做的演示
So the demo I'm gonna do
要使用Attributor这个示例
is I'm gonna take Attributor,
希望大家还记得Attributor
which I, hopefully, you still remember Attributor
大概是三节课以前的内容了
from three lectures ago, or whatever it was.
我们要让Attributor
And we're going to make Attributor
实现自动旋转且旋转后布局正常
so it auto-rotates and looks good.
Attributor就是那个显示文本
Attributor is the thing that had the text
我们可以为其添加轮廓和设置颜色的应用 记得吗
and we could outline it and pick the colors, remember that?
我们要让它实现自动旋转
So we're going to make that do that.
构建Attributor时 我们使用了辅助线
We used the guidelines when we built Attributor,
所以很容易实现
so it's going to be really easy to make this work.
但我要演示一遍
Okay? But I just want to show you what it all looks like,
其实现过程
to make it go.
先讲这一页 等会演示完就下课了
And I'll do this slide because we'll finish with the demo.
周五的时候
On Friday, I'm still hoping
希望大学开发者计划能够正常使用
to get this university developer thing going,
在我将大家加入到计划中之前
again, I'm not going to require any of you
我不会要求大家
to get the thing working on your device
在设备上运行应用
until I can get you into this program,
不用担心
so, no worries there.
加入99美元开发者计划的同学
And those of you who are doing the 99 dollar program,
可以开始使用了
you're all good to go,
希望大家都能在设备上正常运行
hopefully it's all just working for you.
作业截止日期为周一
Your homework, as you know, is due on Monday,
下周我们会讲解滚动视图和表视图
and next week we're going to do scroll view and table view,
我想了一下
actually we probably won't do collection view,
可能不会讲集合视图
the more I think about it,
下周要讲的另外一个内容是iPad
and the other thing we're gonna do next week is iPad.
因为我们到目前为止讲过的都是针对iPhone的
Because everything we've done so far is iPhone,
现在应该讲一讲iPad的内容了
it's time to start doing some iPad.
我们回到Attributor
Okay? So let's go back to Attributor.
在这里打开Xcode 关掉Dropit
So I'm gonna get Xcode up here and let's close Dropit.
停止任务
Stop that task,
回到这里
and so let's go back here,
打开Attributor
and I'm just gonna bring up Attributor, as--
回到上次结束的地方
as we last left it here.
还记得Attributor的界面吗
Remember this is what Attributor's user interface
是这样的
looks like here,
我们今天完全不用看代码
we don't need to see the code at all today,
因为自动布局的全部操作都会在Xcode中完成
because we're gonna do all of this autolayout stuff in Xcode.
我们来看看Attributor现在能做什么
And let's see what Attributor does right now.
运行Attributor 和上次最后一样
So let's run Attributor, just as we left it off.
这就是Attributor
And here it is, here's Attributor,
我们可以做这样的操作 点击这些按钮
remember we can do this kind of stuff, pick these things,
如果对其进行旋转...
and if we rotate, and everyone saw on--
旋转的方法是按住command键
ps the way we rotate it is we hold down the command key,
就是这里这个
it's basically this right here.
command键加箭头键
Command, arrow.
我按下command键加箭头键
Okay? So I'm going to do command arrow.
看起来很糟糕
That looks pretty bad.
对吧
Okay?
实际上是太可怕了
In fact, that's horrible.
因为我们完全不可操控了
Because we've lost all of our control
不能增加轮廓 不能改变颜色
no outline, no colors,
我们在这里什么都不能做
we can't really do anything here.
统计数据这里看起来还好 但是缺失内容了
Stats still looks okay, but it's kind of cutoff,
后面显示的是三个点 这不太好
that's not so good, dot, dot, dot,
所以整个UI的应对措施并不好
so, really this whole UI did not react well,
我们修改一下 让它不要再这样了
and so, let's try and fix it so that it stops doing that,
从某种程度上来说 这有点太简单了
and this is gonna be in some ways almost too easy,
因为我们在拖放这些对象时使用了辅助线
because we dragged all these things out using the guidelines,
我只要点击下面这个像钛战机一样的按钮
so I'm just going to go down here, to the TIE fighter,
然后选择重置为建议约束
and I'm gonna say reset to suggested constraints.
基本上这样就行了
And pretty much that's gonna do it.
再运行一次
So let's just rerun.
我们可以快速浏览一下这些约束
Okay, we could make a quick look at some of these constraints
看看它做了什么
just to see what's it doing, but like this--
把对象面板移开
let's get this out of the way in here.
可以看到文本区域
So, you can see that this thing
与父视图的左边缘绑定
is tied to the superview on the left,
与按钮对齐
it's lined up with the buttons.
与按钮间保持一定间距
It makes a little space in between the buttons,
与顶部保持一定间距
a little space at the top,
基本上添加了我们想要的约束
so it's pretty much doing what we want.
现在再旋转 看看会怎样
Let's see what happens when we rotate now.
这些都还可以正常运行
So we got this, it's still all working, nothing has broken
没有因为增加约束而破坏功能
because of our, putting those constraints in,
旋转一下 看起来很不错
and so we'll rotate, ooh, that looks pretty good!
我还可以添加轮廓
I can still, for example, set my outline,
设置颜色 很好
I can set colors, that's great,
统计数据呢 好多了
stats, ooh, much better.
但是紫色这块不太好
However, this is not so good.
我喜欢紫色 但是没有到这种程度
Okay? I like purple, but not that much. Okay?
所以我们要让它们大小一致
So we've got to make these things all the same size,
让这四个按钮大小一致
we want these four buttons to be the same size, okay?
显然 我们将它们拖进来时没有任何操作
Nothing that we did when we dragged it in, evidently,
能够告诉Xcode这样做
was enough to let Xcode know that.
不过想要实现这条约束特别简单
However, so simple to make that happen,
只要选中这四个按钮
I'm just gonna select these four buttons,
到下面这里
I'm going to go down here
在这个约束添加栏这里
to this little constraint adder right here,
只要点击这个按钮选项
and I'm going to just click this button
将四个按钮设为相同宽度
that says I want these four buttons to have equal widths.
换句话说 我加了约束
In other words, I'm adding the constraint
让它们的宽度相等
that their widths be the same.
我点击"添加三条约束"之后
Okay? So, I just, when I hit add three constraints,
可能会为每一个按钮添加一条约束
it's gonna add one constraint to each of them, probably,
在前面三个按钮上
each of these first three,
让它们和下一个按钮同宽
saying, be the same as the next one over.
我们这样做
We'll do that.
可以看到
You can even see the, see,
就是这样的 宽度相等 看到了吗
here's what they look like, equals. See?
我们运行一下 看行不行
So let's go and run and see if that fixed it.
可以了
And it did.
两种方向都可以
Okay? So, whichever way,
为什么这里不旋转呢
by the way, why does it not rotate here?
因为现在是倒立竖屏
Because this is the upside down, portrait upside down,
在项目设置中
and in our project settings,
我们设置了不支持倒立竖屏
we said we don't support portrait upside down,
所以这里没有旋转
so that's why it just does nothing.
转为倒立竖屏时 什么都不会发生
When you go to portrait upside down, it does nothing.
但是在正向竖屏
But when we stay with portrait right-side up,
和两个横屏模式时
or between either the two of the landscapes,
视图的效果和我们想要的一样
it seems to be doing exactly what we want here in this view.
只有一个问题 如果看一下控制台
And, the only problem is, if we look at our console,
得到了各种错误
we're getting all kinds of errors here.
这看起来可不太好
Okay? This doesn't look too good.
最主要的错误是什么
Okay? And what is this primary error we're getting.
无法同时满足约束
Unable to simultaneously satisfy constraints.
这里看起来很好 没有不对的地方
Okay? So, this looked all good over here, there was no--
没有看到黄色的警告
I don't see anything, there's no yellow things.
如果打开文档大纲
If I bring up my document outline,
这里也没有黄色圆形图标
there's nothing yellow here.
自动布局约束没问题
My autolayout constraints are good!
实际上并不是这样的
Well, actually they're not.
因为它不能
Okay? Because it's unable
在运行时满足约束
to satisfy the constraints at run time.
为什么会这样呢
Okay? Well, why is that happening?
实际上 这里提供了很多信息
Well, it'd actually give you a lot of help
帮助你明白出现错误的原因
as to why that's happening,
把这栏拉宽一点
Make this wider.
这里甚至还给出了ASCII文本
Here, and it gives you even kind of ASCII text,
描述了布局的信息
kind of descriptions of the layouts.
看到了吗 各种对象的布局
You see? How everything's laid out?
我大概已经可以猜到了
But I can probably guess already
因为我刚引发了这个错误
that since I just introduced this error,
所以肯定和我刚做过的操作相关
it has something to do with what I just did.
也就是让按钮的宽度相等
Okay? Which is to make those widths be the same.
我们看一下这些按钮的约束
So, let's take a look at the constraints of these buttons
看看是否能看出来明显的问题
and see if we can see something obvious.
有谁看出来了吗
Okay? Anyone see anything obvious in here?
哪里看起来不太好
That doesn't look very good?
大声说
Speak up.
因为宽度为64是硬编码吗
The width equals 64 is hard coded?
没错
Yeah,
宽度为64 这里是硬编码
the width equals 64 here is hard coded, okay,
这是个魔术数字 不好
that's a magic number, that's bad.
而且 我们知道横屏模式中
And, in fact, we know that when we go to landscape,
宽度不会再是64了
the width's not going to be 64 anyway!
会变宽一些
Right? They all get a little wider in landscape.
这就是问题所在
So this is the problem.
系统想让这些按钮同宽
It's trying to make those buttons all the same width,
而你要让它们的宽度都为64
but you're trying to keep them all 64,
至少是让前三个按钮的宽度都为64
or at least to keep this one and this one and this one 64,
最后一个按钮没有宽度64的约束 不错
this one seems to not have that 64, which is nice.
很容易改好
So this is easy to fix.
只要删除这些宽度64的约束
I'm just gonna delete these width equals 64s,
不是高度64
not the height equals 64.
删掉宽度64这个约束
So let's delete the width equals 64,
删掉这个宽度64约束 还有这个
let's delete this width equals 64, and we'll delete this one.
没有对象变为黄色
Okay? So, this height, nothing turned yellow, okay?
不缺少约束
Nothing was like missing constraints, okay,
全部都有约束指定了 现在再运行
it's all completely still specified, and now if we run.
左右旋转
Okay, and we rotate back and forth.
依旧可以正常运行 按钮会变宽
Still working, still making the buttons wider,
控制台也没有错误提示了
and we're not getting anything in our console here.
有时你的约束
Okay? So sometimes you'll get the constraints,
在Xcode中不会出现什么问题
they won't have any problems in Xcode,
但约束间也可能会有冲突
but you still might have some conflicts,
所以大家应该检查控制台
so you should be looking at your console
看是否有冲突
to see if there's conflicts.
有问题吗
Question?
为什么要保留高度64约束中的魔术数字
why did you keep the height equals 64 magic number?
好的 问题是
Okay, so the question,
为什么要保留高度64约束中的魔术数字
why did I keep the height equals 64 magic number,
非常好的问题
and that's a super good question.
这里使用魔术数字是可以的
Now, it's okay that I have a magic number here.
为什么这里可以呢
And why is that okay here?
因为按钮中没有文本
That's because there's no text in that button.
几乎就像是图像
It's almost like an image, right?
不然的话 它的大小应该是什么
So, what size would it be otherwise?
这里没有
There's nothing--
如果从上到下看看这个视图
if you look from top to bottom in this view,
没有能够指定它的大小的约束
there's nothing that would specify what size is,
文本视图的宽不固定 或者说高不固定
because this is not a fixed width, or height rather,
它有固定高度 上下间距也是
this is a fixed height and so is this and this,
那么它们俩的空间分别是多少呢
but then how much space goes to this and how much goes to this?
将按钮的高度设为64 剩下的空间就是文本视图的
By fixing this one at 64, this one gets the rest.
实际上 我还可以换一种方法
Now, I actually could do this another way.
如果我想让文本视图
If I kind of wanted, you know,
占据大部分空间
the text view to have most of the space
让这些按钮控制在最小尺寸
and this, some of it, and I want it to be a minimum size,
我可以将它的大小
I could actually set the size here to be
设为大于等于某个特定大小
greater than or equal to some particular size,
我可以对它们使用内容压缩优先级
and I could use the content hugging priority
和内容抗压缩优先级
and compression priority between these two
确定哪个对象要得到更大的空间
to make sure that whichever I wanted to get the extra space,
当屏幕变长的时候 就像这样
when it got taller, like this, okay?
我可以定义这个规则
I could make that be defined,
但是将按钮高度设为固定值
but by fixing this one,
保证了文本视图得到全部剩余空间
I'm guaranteeing this one gets all the extra space.
当你用的是图像时
So when you have an image,
我说了有时使用魔术数字是可以的
I said that sometimes a magic number's okay,
通常是针对图像
usually it's when you have an image,
有人绘制了一个插图
some artwork that somebody has drawn
有一个大小约束 就是图像的大小
has a size to it that that's its size.
我想让这些方块保持这个大小
And here, these squares, I want them to be this size,
所以设置了高度约束
so I pick those,
很高兴你问了这个问题 很好的问题
I'm glad you brought that up, that's a good question.
这里我还要处理的是
Okay, the other thing I'm going to do here
右边这一部分
is play around with this,
左边这部分运行正常 不用改了
this is working fine, nothing to change here.
那这边这部分呢
What about this guy over here?
这个挺不好办的
Well, this one's pretty bad.
我将它们拖放在这里时
I kind of dragged these in here
没有使用辅助线一类的东西
without using the, the lines or something,
所以它们是在随机位置上
so they're kind of in random spots.
正好可以演示一下
So here's a good chance to show you
在不使用建议约束的条件下
how to put these things in their place,
如何正确放置控件
not using suggested constraints.
也就是指定控件的位置
Okay? In other words, actually specifying.
我会演示两种方法
So I'll show you both ways to do it.
两种方法都不是建议约束
The both non-suggested constraints.
将轮廓字符这条放在右下角
So let's put outline text in this corner down here,
或者将彩色字符这条放在这里 都可以
and, or we'll put color down there, whichever,
然后让另一条显示在它的上方
and then we'll have the other one stacked on top of it.
所以我希望它们是这个样子的
So I eventually want it to look like this and this,
但我不会用辅助线
but I'm not gonna use the guidelines, okay?
因为我想演示一下其他方法
Because I want to show you a different way to do it.
我选中了彩色字符
So, here I have colorful characters.
目前它没有约束
So it has no constraints, currently,
因为我用重设为建议约束时
because when I said reset suggest constraints,
只针对左边这部分
I was doing that for this guy only, right?
点击这里的钛战机按钮时
When you go here to the TIE fighter,
这里说了是在Attributor视图控制器中
it says in Attributor view controller,
并没有说Stats视图控制器
it doesn't say stats view controller,
所以只针对前者
so it only did it in that one,
这里我没有重置约束
and I didn't reset it here,
所以它们没有约束
so these things have no constraints.
我们将它设置到左下角
So let's set this one to be in this lower left-hand corner
不使用辅助线
without using the guidelines.
方法是使用底部这个按钮
So I'm gonna do that with this guy.
这里这个小按钮
Okay? So this little button right here,
在这里能够指定...
it lets you specify--
宽度相等就是在这里设置的
this is where we did equal widths,
但现在我只选中了一个对象
but here I only have one thing selected,
无法勾选宽度相等这一项
so I can't even pick equal widths,
必须要选中两个以上对象才可以
I'd have to pick two things for that,
但是在上面这里 可以看到
but up here at the top, you'll notice,
可以指定它与周围视图的绑定方式
you can specify that this thing is tied to views around it.
可以是它的父视图或其他视图
Either its superview or its other views.
我还可以选择标准值
Okay? And also, I can pick the standard value here.
就是使用默认值
So I'm using the default value, okay?
通常都要这样做
Which you generally want to do,
你不会想在这里使用魔术数字的
you don't want to have a magic number,
比如这里的100和71
like 100 and 71, in here,
这两个间距就不设置了
but I'm not picking these I beams,
所以它们不会受影响
so those are not going to be affected.
可以看到 系统要添加两条约束
And do you see, it wants to add those two constraints,
就是这两条
that's this one and this one.
我还要说一下这个更新框架
I'm also gonna show you this, update frames.
你可以更新框架
You can update the frames,
换句话说
in other words, move the view
移动当前屏幕上显示的视图
as it currently is showing the scene,
可以是整个容器中的全部框架
either all the frames in the entire container,
或者只是新约束涉及的那些框架
or just the frames that got new constraints.
通常会选择这个
Usually you're going to pick this one,
Items of New Constraints
items of new constraints.
我要点击这个按钮 看看会发生什么
So I'm gonna hit this, and watch what's gonna happen,
彩色字符那个标签
that colorful thing,
会自动跳到左下角
it's going to jump to lower left-hand corner,
和父视图边缘保持标准间距
standard distance away, automatically.
这是设置约束的另一种方法
So that's another way to set the constraints,
看到这里的标准间距了吗
see it put standard distances here,
添加了这些标准间距约束
it's got these standard constraints,
那么它呢
and how about this guy?
我们想让它对齐显示在彩色字符的上方
We want this guy to be lined up on top of this one.
也可以通过这个按钮来实现
We could do that, also, with this, okay?
可以设置间距等等
We could set the I beam here and all that stuff,
但这里我要用control拖拽来实现
but I'm gonna use the control dragging to do that,
我要按住control键
so I'm going to hold down control,
从上面这个标签拖到下面
and I drag from this guy to this guy,
选择垂直间距
and I'm going to have the vertical spacing,
使用shift选择多项
I'm using shift, by the way,
选择垂直间距和左边缘
vertical spacing, and left, in this case, the left edge,
我想让它们对齐
I want those lined up,
然后只要点击返回
and then I just hit return,
系统为我创建了相应的两条约束
and it created me two constraints for that.
下间距和与彩色字符标签对齐
Bottom space and colorful character.
我们看看怎么样
So let's go see what that looks like.
出来了 点击Stats
Alright, so we have this, we do stats,
标签显示在左下角
it stays in the lower left.
横屏和竖屏模式都可以
Whether we're portrait or landscape.
运行得不错 二者始终显示在一起
So that worked perfectly, and they stay stacked on each other.
我还要演示一下 看这个
One thing I want to show you is this, watch this.
选择一大段文字
Let's pick a whole bunch of text here
添加轮廓和颜色
and make it outlined and colored.
转到统计数据
And go to stats.
可以看到 标签内容完整地显示出来了
And you see how these, these nicely show the whole word,
226个彩色字符
226 colorful characters.
也就是说文字没有被切掉
In other words, they don't get cut off.
因为它们用的是内置大小
That's because these two things are their intrinsic size.
如果将其中一个的大小设为固定值会怎样
What happens if, instead, I fix the size of one,
这里大家会看到
and this is why you're gonna see
为什么将内置大小设为固定值不好
these intrinsic size being fixed is bad.
我要将彩色字符这个标签
So I'm gonna take this colorful character one,
设为固定宽度
I'm gonna fix its width
方法是control拖拽到它自己
and I'm gonna do that by control dragging to itself, okay?
选择宽度
And saying width,
还可以通过下面这些按钮实现
I could also do it with these buttons down here.
约束在这里 宽度为157 就是它的当前宽度
And there it is, width equals 157, which is its current width,
我就用这个值了
I'm just gonna leave it that way.
现在运行一下 看看会怎样
Okay, not let's run and see what happens.
看起来没问题 都很好
Okay, so it seems like no problem, everything's good.
但我们再选择大量文字试一下
But let's select a lot of text again.
这就不太好了
Oh, not so good.
它的大小现在不是其内置大小了
You see? Since this thing is not its intrinsic size,
能容下0个字符 但是127个字符就不行了
it couldn't fit when I went to 127 characters instead of 0.
所以就变成了点点点 显示不出来了
Right? So it just went dot, dot, dot, I can't fit.
这是可以控制的
Okay? It always does, you can control this,
但是如果容不下 默认就是三个点
but by default it does this dot, dot, dot, if it can't fit.
大家明白
Okay, so do you see the hazards
固定宽度的危险之处了吗
of having these hardwired widths in here?
删掉它 再运行一次
So if I take this and delete it, and run again,
转到统计数据
now when we go to the stats,
即使内容很多 也能都显示出来
even if we have a lot of stuff, it'll fit. Okay?
还有一个知识点 我快速演示一下
Alright, one other thing I guess I'll show you real quick
如果...
is what happens--
看一下现在的文档大纲
let me show you the document outline piece of this.
没有错误
Okay, so nothing's wrong in here,
但我要制造些错误
but I'm going to make something wrong,
选中轮廓字符标签
let me go to this guy
删掉它的前置对齐约束
and let's delete its aligned leading, okay,
这样它就不再和彩色字符标签对齐了
so it's no longer lined up with this.
这样做之后 注意这条线变黄了
Okay? When I do that, notice this one turns yellow,
因为它代表对象的一条约束
because it is a constraint for an object
出现了问题
that has problems, okay?
所以只要你的对象有问题
So anytime you have an object that has problems,
它的约束都会变为黄色 甚至红色
all its constraints will be yellow, or even red,
如果出现冲突的话
if they're conflicting.
可以看到 这里出现了红色圆形图标
So you can see we've got this little red guy here
说这个对象有问题
saying that there's a problem with this guy,
我们知道问题是什么 对吧
and we know what the problem is, right?
我们不知道它的水平位置
We don't know where it is horizontally,
只知道它的垂直位置
we only know where it is vertically, okay?
我们来做一下
So let's go do that.
这里提示 需要X轴位置的约束
And it says needs constraint for X position,
同样的 我可以点击这个红色图标
again, I can click on this little red thing.
点击添加缺失约束
It'll say add missing constraints,
它很聪明
it's smart,
它知道这两项之前是左对齐的
it knows these two were lined up on the left
这两个标签相邻
it said, it's nearby,
它说 没准它们想要左对齐
it said, oh, it probably wants to be left-aligned,
所以系统就添加了一条左对齐约束
so it put a left align in there.
还有一点 我快速演示一下
One other thing I'll show you real quick,
如果移动了这个标签
you see if moved this guy.
现在这些线都变成黄色了
Okay? You see how now these are yellow,
因为位置不匹配
because this doesn't match up,
这是虚线框的位置
this is where the dashed box is,
同样的 可以在文档大纲中点击它
again, in the outline, if I click this,
系统会提供一些选项
I have these choices up here,
更新框架 让它归位
I'll update the frame to put it back.
还有一点 这样移动之后
One other thing, notice that in all this moving around
这里变为了8 而不是标准间距了
this got set to 8, instead of the standard space,
有时会出现这样的情况
that sometimes happens,
我不知道为什么会丢掉它的默认间距
I'm not really sure why it lost its default space
我们也没有做什么指定它的操作
we didn't really do anything to specify that,
你可以对它进行编辑 选择Select and Edit
but you can edit, select and edit,
甚至还可以...
or you can even, okay,
可以在这里将其修改为Standard
so we could edit here and change this to standard,
或者使用这个小技巧
or watch this little trick.
看见这个图标了吗 双击它
You see that little guy? I'm gonna double click on that.
如果在一个约束上双击
Okay, if you double click on a constraint,
这些选项就会显示在点击位置
all this stuff will appear right you are.
在这里 我要将8修改为
So, in this case, I'm going to switch from 8
Standard Value标准值
to the standard value.
点击返回
Okay? When I hit return,
看来8就是标准值 没有变化
8 is the standard value it turns out, so nothing changed,
只是想为大家演示一下
but just wanted to show you there
可以通过双击约束
how you can double click on a constraint
来设置它的优先级等选项
to set things like its priority and stuff like that.
好了 就是这样
Okay? So that's it!
在作业中
For your homework,
大家只要实现一点自动布局内容
you only have a little bit of autolayout to do
因为你只有...
because you only have a--
除了包含卡牌的视图
besides the card-containing view,
可能还有重新发牌 增加更多卡牌 分数等等 我也不知道
you may have redeal, add more cards, score, I don't know,
因为上次作业中
because I let you delete some of the other stuff
我让大家删掉了一些内容
from previous assignment.
作业中的自动布局应该很简单
So, autolayout should be pretty simple for this,
但学期后面的课程中
but for the rest of this class, all quarter-long,
大家全部都要使用自动布局
you should always be using autolayout.
你的应用应该适用于横屏和竖屏模式
Your app should always work in landscape and portrait
这门课之后的全部内容
for the rest of this class,
所有作业都要这样
okay, all assignments.
布置作业时会说到 但这里先告诉大家
It'll be in the assignments, but, just so you know.
非常感谢
Thank you very much!
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at standford.edu.